<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The grounds and occasions of the controversy concerning the unity of God &amp;c. the methods by which it has been managed, and the means to compose it / by a Divine of the Church of England.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 152 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42243</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G2135</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12220</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11998228</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11998228</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52170</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42243)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52170)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 564:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The grounds and occasions of the controversy concerning the unity of God &amp;c. the methods by which it has been managed, and the means to compose it / by a Divine of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>Nye, Stephen, 1648?-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 53 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and sold by E. Whitlock,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>For discussion of ascription to Stephen Nye see H. McLachlan, The story of a nonconformist library, p. 77.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Omniscience.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52170:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Grounds and Occaſions OF THE CONTROVERSY Concerning the <hi>Vnity of God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>THE METHODS by which it has been managed, AND The MEANS to compoſe it.</p>
            <p>By a Divine of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed, and ſold by <hi>E. Whitlock</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall.</hi> MDCXCVIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:52170:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52170:2"/>
            <head>THE Grounds and Occaſions OF THE CONTROVERSY CONCERNING <hi>The Vnity of God,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THE eminently Learned, Wiſe, and Good Biſhop of <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>Connor, Jeremy Taylor,</hi> having affirm'd and prov'd from expreſs, clear, and full Atteſtations of Scripture, from the Reaſonableneſs of the thing, from the Teſtimonies of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and later Schoolmen, that all the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith are plainly ſet down in Scripture, did not yet ſcruple to acknowledg, <q>That there were ſtill in Scripture innumerable Places containing in them great Myſteries; but then thoſe Myſteries, he thought, were ſo involv'd with Clouds and Darkneſs, ſo cover'd with Allegories and Garments of Rhetorick, that God may ſeem to have left them as Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of our Induſtry, as Arguments of our Imperfections, Incentives to our Longings after the cleareſt Revelations of Eternity, and as Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions and Opportunities of Mutual Charity and Toleration.</q>
            </p>
            <p>That the Myſterious Paſſages of Scripture, are Trials ever like to find Work for our Induſtry, and convincing Arguments of our Imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is evident from the little ſatisfaction which the many various at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted Interpretations have given; and I queſtion not but this Reflec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may incline devouter Minds ardently to long for the brighter Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52170:3"/>
of Eternity: but how few are they who make the obſcure Myſteries of Scripture, Occaſions and Opportunities of Mutual Charity and Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration? In truth it is but reaſonable to judg that the All-wiſe God deſign'd them for this good end; but the general Event which has accidentally follow'd, through the Indiſpoſition of unwiſe and ill-natur'd Men, is, that they are made Occaſions of venting bitter hatred, and wreaking zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Malice one upon another.</p>
            <p>Could Religious Controverſies be manag'd without intemperate Heat, breach of Friendſhip and good Neighbourhood, the advantages iſſuing thence might perhaps be more and greater than could be eaſily eſteem'd and numbred; we ſhould certainly reap Fruits worthy our Induſtry and Study, either by improvements of our Knowledg, or ſenſe of our Ignorance; we ſhould happily teach, or at leaſt civilly uſe one another: but if we are forſaken of common Prudence, as well as Chriſtian Charity, we ſhall turn all our Diſputes about Religion, and <hi>[when we are forbid them]</hi> every thing elſe into the Inſtruments of barbarous Cruelty, and thereby create a greater miſchief to the Body Politick, whereof we are all Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, than a wiſe Conqueror would compel us to ſuffer, or a fair Enemy wiſh.</p>
            <p>It is out of an honeſt deſire of being ſerviceable, not to demonſtrate what is the certain true ſenſe of a Myſterious Article, [I would ſooner promiſe to ſolve all the puzling Phaenomena in Nature, or fix the time for the Downfal of the <hi>Turk,</hi> and Converſion of the <hi>Jews</hi>] but to prevent the miſchievous Conſequences of various Interpretations, that I am going to conſider, <list>
                  <item>I. What has rais'd the Diſputes at preſent agitated among us.</item>
                  <item>II. What has inflam'd them to that dangerous Exceſs, which in time 'tis fear'd may diſturb the publick Quiet.</item>
                  <item>III. What's the proper way to remedy the Miſchiefs which have hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd, and to prevent farther.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>It is to me evident that the original of our preſent Diſputes can be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd to no one Cauſe; many Perſons, Eccleſiaſticks and others, diverſly mov'd, have ingag'd in them. There is one ſort of Men, who have been ſometimes diſtinguiſh'd by the Name of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> and by angry Adverſaries reproachfully call'd <hi>Socinians;</hi> but [to deal juſtly on all ſides] who ought to be numbred with the Orthodox, becauſe they not only embrace the Doctrines of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but alſo are contented to uſe her School-terms, which they once thought, and do ſtill think
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52170:3"/>
not ſo fit to expreſs her ſound Doctrines. Theſe Perſons, as to me ſeems probable, have engag'd in our Religious Controverſies,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Out of an averſion from taking things upon truſt. This Motive muſt be allow'd to be reaſonable and juſt, becauſe he that gives up his Faith to human Authority, is beholden to his good Fortune, whenever the Opinions which fall to his lot, have any thing of truth or uſefulneſs in them; and as often as they happen to be illgrounded and noxious, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves all the evil Conſequences which he ſuffers by them; for if he had made uſe of his Reaſon before he gave his Aſſent, there was at leaſt a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability that he might have known better, and guided himſelf more ſafely. The <hi>Bereans</hi> are commended in Scripture who would not take things upon truſt, no not from the Mouth of an Apoſtle; which is enough to juſtify, without farther arguing, all them who are concern'd in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Controverſies, mov'd thereunto by an averſion from taking things up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on truſt. If I were writing to do ſervice to theſe Orthodox Unitarians, [for that muſt be granted to be their Character, now they have explain'd themſelves, and taken off the jealouſy which the Church had conceiv'd of them] if I were writing purpoſely to do them ſervice, I might here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiate in liberal Praiſes due to that noble Diſpoſition of Mind, which takes nothing upon truſt: We are beholden to it for all the great Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Knowledg, which ſerve the Neceſſities and Comforts of Life; and not only ſo, but methinks we owe to it our very Chriſtian Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxy it ſelf: for an eaſy implicit Believer will never ſtand with his Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream, be it Alcoran, or what it will, which he is required to ſubſcribe; but the wary Examiner, who ſearches the Scripture that he may ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things are as the Church teaches, no ſooner perceives the truth of her Articles, but he holds unmoveably ſtedfaſt to them, and unfeignedly venerates his holy Mother. But this is not my buſineſs now: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another Motive, which I am perſwaded has influenc'd theſe Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Unitarians to enter into Religious Controverſy, is an honeſt deſire to be ſerviceable to the Church, and uſeful to well-diſpos'd leſs-knowing Chriſtians, by inſtructing and informing them. Whether theſe Perſons are Eccleſiaſticks or Laymen it matters not much; for I ſuppoſe it will be granted, that it is lawful for one Man to inform and inſtruct his Friend, Neighbour, or Countryman, either in private Diſcourſe, or publick Print, tho he be not a Miniſter of the Goſpel, or perhaps not Epiſcopally ordain'd.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I will not ſay but that theſe Unitarians may have been thruſt upon Controverſy by a forward zeal to defend the Myſterious Doctrines of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52170:4"/>
Church, againſt the Heatheniſh Interpretations of ſome eminent unwary Tritheiſts. Zeal in defence of Doctrines which are certainly true, or at leaſt unfeignedly believ'd to be ſo, and againſt Errors really pernicious, or generally ſuſpected as ſuch by good Men; if it ſpend its force only to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the former, and to refute the latter, abſtaining from all Illegal, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious and Unchriſtian Treatment of erroneous Perſons, may paſs for a vertuous and laudable temper of Mind. Men give an aſſent, an unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed aſſent to Doctrines, becauſe they believe them to be true; and they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to perſwade others of the truth of thoſe Doctrines whereof they are perſwaded themſelves, becauſe they ſuppoſe that the ſame may be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial to others, as well as to themſelves: On the contrary, they ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly diſpute againſt thoſe Doctrines, which they imagine to have an evil influence, prejudicing the nobler Intereſts of Mankind. To me then it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that the arguing and diſputing Temper is cheriſh'd and prompted by good Nature; but if Wiſdom does not direct, and Charity accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it, if it grows wild and imperious, and uſes them ill, whom it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not convince, it ceaſes to be a laudable vertuous Temper, and becomes quite another thing. Now whether theſe Unitarians have vindicated the Myſterious Doctrines of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by proper cogent Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, and in an obliging Chriſtian manner, without illegal injurious treatment of Diſſenters; that's a Queſtion which ought not raſhly to be determin'd for or againſt them. That I may more impartially deal in my Cenſures, I defer the Conſideration of it till my method ſhall lead me to conſider alſo how proper and how cogent have been the Arguments; how winning and civil their manner of handling them, who have made it their buſineſs to oppoſe theſe unfortunate, but perhaps not juſtly ſuſpected Unitarians: for to ſpeak freely, I am afraid that all which either of them muſt pretend to, is to have committed the feweſt Miſtakes, and to have treſpaſs'd leaſt againſt the righteous equitable Laws of Chriſt, and the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally accepted Rules of good Manners.</p>
            <p>I have now noted all that I can probably imagine to have prompted the <hi>Orthodox</hi> Unitarians to enter into the Religious Controverſies which are at preſent under debate. Methinks it is too hard to judg as ſome do, that they have been ſpurr'd on by a vain Oſtentation of Learning; tho thus much is evident, without a ſtock not contemptible they could not have done what they have: but to ſay that their Writers are mercenary, and hir'd to the Work, looks as like an impertinent Slander as can be; but to ſuppoſe them hir'd, which I don't believe, tho' I can't prove the contrary, I would fain ask, where's the unpardonable crime, to be hir'd to write in defence of this or that Explication which the Church
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52170:4"/>
gives of an Article that's obſcure, and underſtood but in part? If any Man will hire me to that Work, which agrees with honeſt Principles, and exceeds not my poor Abilities, I am not aſham'd to declare that I am at his Service, ready to be commanded at a reaſonable Rate.</p>
            <p>There is another Diviſion of Diſputants engag'd in Religious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy, but which fall into many a Subdiviſion; all which Subdiviſions are in open profeſſion, and moſt of them in truth and reality of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as well as the Unitarians, tho they are ſometime un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſely content to prove their Title to that Honour by ſo weak an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as their differing from the Unitarians; and when they have done, very few of them differ from the Unitarians, except in terms Scholaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, peculiar Phraſe and manner of Expreſſion, which ſmall matter is alſo now very well accommodated.</p>
            <p>This Diviſion of Diſputants, with all their Subdiviſions, may be compriz'd under the general diſtinction of Nominaliſts and Realiſts; the former are of the Church, and know themſelves to be ſo; the latter are meer Heathens, as far as Polytheiſm goes, tho they know it not: we are bound in Charity to believe they know it not, becauſe they profeſs to be of the Church. Both the Nominaliſts and Realiſts engag'd againſt the ſuſpected Unitarians, mov'd thereunto, as may be gueſs'd from their Writings,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By a profound Reverence for Authority. To do theſe Gentlemen juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice as well as the former, this Motive is not to be raſhly condemn'd, nor yet can it be well allow'd, without nearly examining what is here meant by Reverence, and what degrees of Reverence are here ſpoken of: Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by Reverence, a good opinion, and high eſteem of the Wiſdom of the Antients, of Fathers and Councils, of modern Convocations of pious and dignified, learned and wealthy Men, methinks it is a juſtifiable Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, a Motive alſo to which we are naturally inclin'd: for we are born only with a nobler Form, and a Docility above other Creatures; and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the firſt advances of our Knowledg, it is hardly poſſible for us to think of ever becoming, like the Royal Pſalmiſt, wiſer than our Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: When our Reaſon is grown manly, and can go alone, <hi>i. e.</hi> of it ſelf compare Ideas, examine their Agreement and Diſagreement, thence draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing farther uſeful Concluſions, ſtill we are juſtly inclin'd to have a great Reſpect for our Teachers, and Men of Fame that went before us; and cannot, nay ought not to endure to have their Doctrines condemn'd as erroneous, without fair and full evidence againſt them. When Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence chances to acquaint us with any notices, about which our Anceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, or now living Teachers, have been miſtaken, there is ſtill a Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52170:5"/>
due to them, a Reverence that ſhould reſtrain us from expoſing them, a Reverence that ſhould guide us modeſtly to repreſent what our own ſtudy and obſervance hath diſcover'd; and 'tis but an honeſt and grateful Reverence to their Wiſdom, to vindicate all their Concluſions, which our own Reaſon apprehends to have been fairly drawn from juſt Premiſes. Wherefore all thoſe Writers that have ingag'd in Religious Controverſy, mov'd by ſuch Sentiments as theſe, their Reverence for Authority becomes them, and juſtifies their Undertaking; but what is beyond this, is Exceſs and Extravagance, and it were ſtrange if the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts of ſuch Motives ſhould be regular and even, reaſonable and uſeful. It is notorious Exceſs, and wild Extravagance, to make Gods of Men, and equal Human Authority to Divine. The Doctrines of Fathers, the Canons of Councils, the Decrees of Popes, the Confeſſions of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Churches, may, 'tis true, be reaſonably defended by any Man who is ſincerely perſwaded, that the ſame are truly ſtated, righteouſly or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd, wiſely decreed, and well drawn up: But when any Doctrines or Canons, Decrees or Confeſſions, are defended, not for ſake of their own Truth and Excellence, but in reverence to the Authority of the Authors, a Reverence is paid them above what they can deſerve, becauſe a greater cannot be paid to God Almighty. We can but ſubmit our Judgments to the Revelations of God; and it is lawful for us to examine, nay 'tis our commendation to examine how far thoſe Hiſtories are to be truſted which give us an account of his Revelations: having once ſatisfy'd our ſelves in this point, [and as to the Hiſtories of the Old and New Teſtament, we have fair and full Evidence, that's my Opinion, and I am ſure the Unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians grant it] we have then nothing to do but to examine [with the beſt skill we have in Languages, and Cuſtoms of the old <hi>Jews,</hi> and firſt <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> by regarding the Genius, Style, and Deſign of Sacred Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] what is the true and proper ſignification of the Words which we read, what ſenſe ariſes from them. Contradictions to natural Reaſon cannot be the true ſenſe of the words, Difficulties may; ſuch is the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Reſurrection: if we ſubmit our Judgments in any caſe but this, where we are ſure of a Divine Revelation, and where we are ſure of the ſenſe of the ſacred Penman's words, we pay an exceſſive Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Authority of Men; but I believe that thoſe Gentlemen who profeſs to ſubmit their Judgments to the Church, have no other aim, but to court <hi>the Church</hi> her favour, or cheat her inſpection with a Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. There's no avoiding ſuch a thought as this, when the ſolemn and publick Judgment and Declaration of a Vice-chancellor and Heads of one of our Univerſities, condemning <hi>the Doctrine of three infinite diſtinct
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52170:5"/>
Minds and Subſtances in the Trinity, as Falſe, Impious, and Heretical, contrary to the Doctrine of the Catholick Church, and of the Church of</hi> England, is made a Jeſt of, and rejected with bold, contemptuous and angry Railery. All that the Church of <hi>England</hi> requires of us is, I humbly conceive, ſuch a Reverence and Eſteem as I firſt deſcrib'd, a wiſe Submiſſion, a Reverence join'd with Honeſty, and a good Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, a Submiſſion, according as may be gather'd from the 20th of her 39 Articles; becauſe ſhe does not, as ſhe ought not, ordain any thing contrary to God's Word written; becauſe ſhe expounds Scripture, one place conſonant to another; becauſe ſhe is a faithful Keeper of Holy Writ, decrees nothing againſt the ſame; and beſides the ſame enforces nothing as neceſſary to Salvation. The Church does not pretend to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility; the moſt eminent, Sons ſhall I ſay, or Fathers of the Church, look upon her Articles as Forms in a comprehenſive Latitude, drawn up for Peace ſake; and very conſcious are they that the Church of the laſt Age was <hi>Calviniſt,</hi> the Church of the preſent Age <hi>Arminian,</hi> and all the while it was Church of <hi>England:</hi> but when bold Opiniators ſhall not be content to keep themſelves within the accountable bounds of prudential Latitude, but ſtart odd Notions, not at all diſtinguiſhable from Heatheniſh Polytheiſm, then they who diſpute againſt them enter into Religious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy, mov'd thereunto by a very juſt Motive. But perhaps it may be urg'd, that the Polytheiſts did not begin the Quarrel: Well, ſuppoſe it, what will they gain by that Plea, if ſtill their Doctrine is no other than Polytheiſm? And what if it ſhould appear that the Unitarians gave the firſt occaſion of Diſpute; this will create no Prejudice againſt them, in the Minds of conſidering Men: for as far as I can perceive, they took Exceptions not againſt the Articles, but the Scholaſtical Terms of the Church; and drove at nothing farther, than that thoſe difficult Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which are called Myſteries, might be expreſs'd as far as the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject would admit, in words plain and intelligible; and when that could not be, in the very Phraſe of Scripture. The Unitarians, if I take them right, cannot yet ſubmit their Judgment, ſo as not to prefer Scripture-Phraſe before Scholaſtick Terms; tho they are ſuch lovers of Peace, that it has been again and again declar'd, that when nothing is meant by all thoſe Terms of Art which is contrary to Reaſon, or not conſonant to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, they will not contentiouſly decline the uſe of them. They have ſaid as much in ſome of their Prints, and I ſhould not do them juſtice, if I did not take notice of it. They are alſo ready to pay due reverence to the Church, becauſe of her great Candour and Moderation in not exac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from good Chriſtians a ſubmiſſion of Judgment as to the uſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52170:6"/>
Rites and Ceremonies; ſomething more hardly once ſhe treated them, but now (God be thanked) ſhe is come to a true Chriſtian Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; ſo that I reckon, the Toleration which Parliamentary Authority has indulg'd, is enjoy'd by conſcientious Separatiſts with the conſent of the Church; for it were uncharitable to ſuſpect that ſhe is not the ſame now, as a while ago in the time of her danger: And therefore I think that thoſe warmer Zealots, who entertain their Auditories with Invectives againſt the Toleration, do not only ſlight the Authority of King and Parliament, but alſo bring a Scandal upon the Church. It is but juſt to believe that the Church is pleas'd with the Toleration for this other reaſon, becauſe ſhe gets more by that, than ever ſhe did by violence; for it is viſible that our Parochial Churches are fuller now than when we compell'd Men to come in. But enough of this, tho it is not altogether out of the way; for this alſo tends to declare on what accounts a reverential eſteem is due to the Church; and on what reſpects the vindication of her Honour is a juſt Motive of entring into Religious Controverſy: but a blind ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Judgment to all that the Church already has decreed, or may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree hereafter, is a ſenſleſs ſlaviſh Stupidity. An implicit Faith in all her Articles, is more than ſhe does require; a taking up always with the firſt obvious, literal Grammatical Senſe, is more than the moſt, and the moſt learned Deacons, Prieſts and Biſhops themſelves do.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Perſons, of whom I have been ſpeaking, were prompted, as may be gather'd from their Prints, to enter into Religious Controverſy by an indignation againſt all Innovations in Religion. As ſpecious a look as this Motive has, it muſt be very well circumſtanc'd, before it can be allow'd for a juſt and reaſonable one; for it happens many times, that the Innovation is but ſurmis'd and ſuſpected; and perhaps there would not be half the Differences which there are in the Church, if words which have not all of them determinate and diſtinct Ideas, if terms of Art and equivocal Phraſes were expounded, and ſixt by exact and plain Definitions. Foreign <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are apt to ſuſpect that the Church of <hi>England</hi> favours the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, becauſe ſhe expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes her ſelf by that ambiguous Phraſe, <hi>Real Preſence;</hi> they are afraid leſt Real Preſence ſhould ſignify Corporeal Preſence: But when the Church avows, that ſhe does not uſe the word <hi>Real</hi> in that ſenſe, but means on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a <hi>Spiritual</hi> Preſence, apprehended and enjoy'd by Faith, the occaſion of diſpute is remov'd, and all that can be ſaid againſt the Church, is, that her Language is not ſo proper, as her Faith is pure. Therefore that celebrated Hugonot <hi>Jurieu,</hi> was more angry than the Cauſe deſerv'd, when he join'd Tranſubſtantiation and Real Preſence together, and call'd 'em both Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52170:6"/>
which harſh Cenſure cannot be return'd upon his Accompliſhment of Prophecies, for that's an ingenious, learned, pretty thing: the Events of Hiſtory have an agreeable reſemblance to the Apocalyptick Emblems to which he applies them; but for all that, I believe there's not one word of truth in his interpretative Accompliſhment. By the Form of Abſolution in the Viſitation of the Sick, one might be apt to ſuſpect, that it was the Doctrine of our Church, that God has given power to our Prieſts that now are, to forgive ſins; but yet the generality of our Prieſts abhorring deluſive Prieſt-craft, make no more of it than a meer Declaration, that God forgives the Sinner, ſuppoſing he be truly penitent: When they have thus explain'd themſelves, no Body can quarrel their Doctrine; and who would fall out with them for an aukward way of expreſſing it? Ever give me Catholick, Orthodox Doctrine, tho vail'd under obſcure and leſs proper Phraſe, rather than groſs affected Tritheiſm, openly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow'd, and in diſtinct plain words expreſs'd, in words and phraſe ſo clear and proper, that every underſtanding unbiaſs'd Reader may at firſt ſight apprehend it. Now by explaining and defining, the occaſion of Diſpute is remov'd; indeed ſome Diſputants define <hi>ignotum per ignotius,</hi> one ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure ambiguous word, term, phraſe, by another more obſcure and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguous: they mend the matter well; but full, plain and clear Definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons make ſhort work of Controverſy: The Diſputants quickly ſee by this means where 'tis they differ, if ſo be they do differ; for not rarely it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, they diſcover that they were of one and the ſame mind, tho they did not expreſs their thoughts after one and the ſame manner. I am very much miſtaken, or this is the very Caſe between the ſuſpected Unitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and the Nominal Orthodox Trinitarians who ſuſpected them: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed as to the Realiſts, there is a wide difference between them, and both the former; their Tritheiſm is Innovation with a Witneſs, and a juſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive for their Oppoſers to engage in Religious Controverſy. Again it may happen, that the Innovation comes to no more than the reviving a long-buried Truth, or the rubbing the ruſt off from a corrupted Uſage: for Truths certain and uſeful have run like Rivers under ground for ſeveral Ages, and then their firſt appearance afterwards may be call'd Innovation; but that will not juſtify any Man's contending for his old Errors; no, tho his old Errors have liv'd for ſeveral Ages. The eating and drinking the Body and Blood of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt by Faith, t'other Day was a meer Innovation; yet I do not believe that our Real Trinitarians will ſay, that the Anthropophagous Romaniſts, the human Fleſh and Blood-eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Papiſts,</hi> had reaſon with Fire and Sword to oppoſe it. The cry of Innovation is ſometimes made uſe of, to ſecure a beloved falſe Doctrine
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52170:7"/>
from being contradicted; a ſuperſtitious cheating Practice from being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermin'd. Where a preſent Eſtabliſhment is without fault, no Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can be ſo; but a departing from the Language of the Schools, is not the ſame thing as departing from the Faith. Yet that our Differences may be accommodated in ſome tolerable manner, let ſound Religion, ſay I, be taught in barbarous Language; better ſo, than Tritheiſm cloth'd with words pure and proper, and phraſe elegantly plain; for that's but like <hi>Martial</hi>'s fine Amber-Box, with nothing but a Viper and a dead Fly in it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Both Realiſts and Nominaliſts, as themſelves profeſs, and I believe, honeſtly have entred into Religious Controverſy to vindicate the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion, the main Foundation of which, they once (by miſtake) ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily thought that the Unitarians were undermining, and labouring to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow. It is good to be jealous for the honour of the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; but nevertheleſs it is a fault, and a very unchriſtian one, to charge any Man unjuſtly: for an unjuſt Charge of this high nature, robs innocent Perſons of the Comforts and Advantages which they might chance to have in the good opinion of others; and not only ſo, but expoſes them to the dire Effects of that Zeal, which is too hot ever to have mercy, and too paſſionate ever to conſider matters calmly, deliberately, and as they ought to be conſider'd. When the Realiſts and Nominaliſts firſt ſuſpected the Unitarians of entertaining ſuch wicked and deteſtable thoughts, as to undermine and ſubvert the main Foundation of the Chriſtian Religion, it would have extreamly become them to have carefully weigh'd what are the ſure and certain Truths, which may be reaſonably call'd the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Chriſtian Religion; and what are the leſs certain Doctrines and Speculations, concerning which, Men that lead vertuous and Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Lives, are differently perſwaded: But now in their anger and their haſte, they have condemn'd the Unitarians as Hereticks, for not giving the true ſenſe of ſome Articles, whoſe true ſenſe they themſelves have not yet found out, or are not agreed upon. One would think that a miſtaken Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of an obſcure Article did not tend to the Subverſion of the Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Religion, but they have judg'd it otherwiſe; yet to do them right, for furious mercileſs Judges, they uſe as much equity as could be wiſh'd, carrying on their ſevere Cenſures with a remarkable Impartiality. The Tritheiſtick Trinity (ſays one of them) is worſe even than <hi>Socinianiſm:</hi> The Nominal Trinity (ſays another) is as bad; in which laſt Cenſures, I ſhall not contradict them: but one thing I muſt remark, <hi>viz.</hi> That when the Purpoſes in which Men agree are none of the beſt, the gaining their Point is but removing an Obſtacle which hinders them from vexing one
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52170:7"/>
another. There are ſome great Men, who (out of what Chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, neither I, nor they can tell) would have the Unitarians be Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks by themſelves, and by conſequence burnt by themſelves, without the company of any of them who commit the very ſame, or a more hainous fault: For which purpoſe they ſolicit the Magiſtrates, after the manner of Inquiſitors, <hi>Omni affectu quo poſſint,</hi> but without the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſy of the Inquiſitors; for theſe great Men of ours call for Fire in plain words, which the other mean when they require Mercy, and to juſtify the Exemption of whom they pleaſe from Hereſy and the Stake. T'other day this Dream was told;—<q>A Man may be very right in the belief of an Article, and yet be miſtaken in his Explication of it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I call this a Dream, meaning no diſreſpect in the World to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, for <hi>quandoque bonus dormitat Homerus,</hi> but becauſe it appears at the very firſt ſight an inconſiſtent Notion; now pleaſing Dreams Men are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to part with, therefore a Friend is call'd in to give credit to this; but as ill luck would have it, all which that Friend ſays, is <q>That a Man may quit his Explication, without parting with the Article it ſelf: That is, Dr. <hi>Sh—</hi> may quit his Explication, and ſo may eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry other Realiſt, without parting with the Article of the Trinity.</q> But under favour, he that quits the <hi>true</hi> Explication, quits the Article it ſelf, or it is impoſſible to quit it. To ſpeak ſeriouſly, one would wonder how it could enter into the thoughts of a wiſe Man being awake, to imagine that an Article might be rightly believ'd, that was not rightly underſtood. If it be objected, that I alter the Caſe, and ſhould have worded it— that was not rightly explain'd: I reply, The thing is the ſame; for I preſume that the Author from whom I beg leave to diſſent, will obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gingly grant me, That the Explainer, whom he would ſave from He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy, underſtands as he explains: I am ſure he's a Knave if he does not; and ſpeculative Hereſy is an innocent thing, in compariſon with practical Knavery. To declare publickly that an Article may be rightly believ'd, which is not rightly underſtood! if an Unitarian, or any Friend of theirs had done it, without queſtion he had been plentifully reproach'd. Mr. <hi>J. E.</hi> B. D. would not have miſs'd the occaſion, but have enrich'd his laſt Rhapſody of railing, with Exclamations argumentative, as well as ill-natur'd. How! an Article rightly believ'd, tho not rightly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood! —To ſee what ſenſeleſs ſhifts theſe pretenders to Reaſon take up with, to ſave their Heterodoxes from the imputation of Hereſy, and themſelves from the peril of the Stake! What Idea can there be had of ſo ſelf-contradicting a Propoſition? Indeed to ſuch a ſharp Reproof as
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52170:8"/>
this, I don't ſee what could have been reply'd by any Unitarian of them all, or by Mr. <hi>Lock,</hi> or Mr. <hi>Toland</hi> either [as much Friends as they are (tho neither ſide knows it) to the Unitarians.] But then thoſe Gentlemen are not capable of ſuch an elevated Thought; it is not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for any one to riſe ſo high, but a vaſt-read, profound Scholar, who does not judg concerning the Truth of a Propoſition, by the Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Diſagreement of the Ideas contain'd in it, but by a ſort of Reaſon, which what it is, and how it operates, no Conception can be had, nor Account given. But whatever Mr. <hi>J. E.</hi> would have done had this contradictory Notion been ſtarted by an Unitarian, I ſhall deal gently with it, obſerving only, that, for whoſe ſake ſoever it was made pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, it will ſave all that Aſſent and Conſent to an Article, as it lies in the Words of the Church, of what Denomination ſoever they are, and how plainly contradictory ſoever their Explanations; it will ſave all alike, all, or none. But the Unitarians want not this Plea to defend their Cauſe, for they profeſs to believe the Article of the Trinity; nay, and what is more, they explain that Article to the very ſame Senſe as do the Nominaliſts, for Peace ſake ſubmitting even to the Scholaſtick Terms, which they cannot like ſo well as the very Phraſe of Scripture. Now I cannot imagine how theſe Unitarians, ſo very orthodox, and ſo exactly conformable to the Church, can be left alone in the lurch for Hereticks, unleſs it be prov'd, that, as one Man may be right in the Belief of an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, tho he be wrong in the Explication; ſo another may be right in the Explication of an Article, tho he be miſtaken in the Belief of it. But after all theſe things which may be righteouſly pleaded in behalf of the Unitarians, it muſt not be denied but that their Adverſaries had a juſt Motive to enter into religious Controverſy, while they ſuſpected them of labouring to undermine the Chriſtian Religion; only their Adverſaries were to blame, that they did not more calmly and leiſurely examine the Meaning of thoſe Paſſages, whatſoever they were, at which they took Offence. I purpoſe to offer ſomething now, to clear all Suſpicions that the Nominaliſts may chance to entertain of the Unitarians: as for the Realiſts, no Accommodation can ever be between them and true Chriſtians; great Men, out of the abundance of their Charity, may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give the Tritheiſm of thoſe Heatheniſh Writers, but by all their Wit and Learning they can never make Three infinite Minds to be but One God: nevertheleſs, I am content that they be forgiven, only I would not have ſo much Charity waſted to forgive them, that there be no Equity left for ſincerer Chriſtians. In order to clear the Suſpicions which the Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naliſts may chance to entertain of the Unitarians, that ſo there may be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52170:8"/>
no Simultates between them, no evil Grudgings, no baſe Language, no unchriſtian Reviling, I ſhall conſider, 1. What manner of Perſons thoſe are, who of late have been diſtinguiſh'd by the Name of Unitarian. 2. What is the Tendency of their Doctrines. And this I propound to do, not by way of Anſwer to all the falſe and foul Imputations which are vomited up by Mr. <hi>Burgeſs,</hi> Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> or that over-bold Poetaſter who makes ſo bold with the Almighty, as to ſubſcribe himſelf God's moſt humble, moſt faithful, and devoted Servant, (but I ſuppoſe that that Gentleman will excuſe himſelf, and ſay, all the World may know he did but complement) but in hopes to ſatisfy thoſe fairer Diſputants, ſuch as Dr. <hi>Pain</hi> and Mr. <hi>Norris,</hi> whom, by their Chriſtian Candor and Equity, one may with more Reaſon conclude heartily to believe the holy Religion which they profeſs. Yet it will not be proper to ſpeak to the firſt Head, until I have premis'd a word to inform the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of what ſtanding theſe Unitarians are. When the Papiſts ask the Proteſtants, Where was your Church before <hi>Luther?</hi> the Proteſtants, by way of Reply, pretend to find Chriſtians through all Ages, tho of divers Denominations, who are recorded to have held the ſame Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with them: in like manner, the Opinions which are at this day charg'd upon the Unitarians, may be trac'd up from Age to Age, to the very next times to the Apoſtles, and by their early Aſſerters were vouch'd as truly Chriſtian and Apoſtolical; and in ſeveral Ages a great majority of Chriſtian Profeſſors holding the ſame, they then went for Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox. But our Church of <hi>England,</hi> bearing a great Reverence for Antiquity, is very zealous for the Retention of ſome old Philoſophical Terms, yet as nice and careful in explaining the ſame according to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Reaſon; tho at the ſame time, ſhe, in the Perſons of her moſt Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Sons, is reproach'd by a few backſliding Tritheiſtick Realiſts, as if ſhe agreed with thoſe antient Hereticks ſaid to be the Founders and Predeceſſors of the Unitarians. The Unitarians themſelves, I mean the Engliſh of late ſo call'd, think it an Injury to be term'd <hi>Ebionites, Alogians, Arians, Photinians,</hi> &amp;c. or indeed any thing but Chriſtians; but when they are reproach'd by thoſe Names of diſtinction, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forbear noting that the very Apoſtles Creed has lain under the Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of <hi>Arianiſm, Photinianiſm,</hi> &amp;c. God knows how juſtly; for we have ſome Orthodox Doctrines, which if they are contained in that Creed, are yet ſo covertly contain'd there, that it is not every ordinary Reaſoner that can eſpy them, and by a long Train of juſt Conſequences deduce them, and bring them into light. By the Apoſtles Creed how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, and by the Holy Scriptures, the Unitarians are always willing to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52170:9"/>
be tried, and mean not to make a Peace-diſturbing Schiſm from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> at leaſt not as long as the chief Doctors of the Church profeſs, That by none of her Homilies, Creeds, or Canons, they mean any ſuch thing as a Tritheiſtick Trinity, a Trinity with three diſtinct infinite Minds. The preſent Term of Reproach (with which ſome Men, for want of better Argument, hope to confound the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians) is <hi>Socinian.</hi> Now it muſt be confeſt, That the Unitarians think honourably of <hi>Socinus;</hi> but yet they do not eſpouſe his whole Scheme, nor any thing of his Scheme, becauſe it is his; nor any thing more of his Scheme than is eſpous'd by their <hi>Arminian</hi> Nominaliſt Brethren, who are a great majority of the Church, tho the Animadverter may not love to bear of it. <hi>Socinus</hi>'s Life is in Print among us, both Latin and Engliſh: the Memory of the Man is frequently revil'd; but I do not hear that his Adverſaries undertake to refute the hiſtorical Account which the Polonian Knight has giv'n of him. Mr. <hi>Bidle,</hi> in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, has theſe Words of <hi>Socinus,</hi> 
               <q>He took the ſame courſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate the Goſpel, that Chriſt and the Apoſtles had done before him, forſaking his Eſtate, and his neareſt Relations, and undergoing all manner of Labours and Hazards to draw Men to the Knowledg of the Truth: He had no other End of all his Undertakings, than the Glory of God and Chriſt, it being impoſſible for Calumny it ſelf to aſperſe him with the leaſt Suſpicion of worldly Intereſt. He, of all Interpreters, explaineth the Precepts of Chriſt in the ſtricteſt manner, and windeth up the Lives of Men to the higheſt Strain of Holineſs.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Author of the <hi>Growth of Error</hi> makes it an Article againſt <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> that he accus'd the Reformed of immoral Practices, and boaſted of the Holineſs of his own Followers. But what ſays that Author? Was <hi>Socinus</hi>'s Accuſation unjuſt, or his Boaſting raſh and ill grounded? Why, he ſays, <hi>Meiſner</hi> anſwer'd <hi>Socinus;</hi> but it ſeems he confeſſes too, that <hi>Schlichtingius</hi> defended him. Upon the whole matter, to ſpeak impartially, Excepting that the foreign Unitarians are recorded to have ſometimes dealt hardly with one another upon account of their diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Perſwaſions concerning worſhipping Jeſus Chriſt, it does not appear that their Lives were wicked and unchriſtian. Here in <hi>England,</hi> Men that know little of them, or have Ends in traducing them, load them with heavy Imputations; but impartial Men abroad, who have known and obſerv'd them, notwithſtanding they differ from them, do yet bear honourable Teſtimony to their Piety and Vertue. Monſieur <hi>Stoop</hi> a Proteſtant Officer in the French Army, in his <hi>Religion of the Dutch, Anno</hi> 1673. gives this Account of the Socinians in <hi>Holland:</hi> 
               <q>They
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52170:9"/>
have their ſecret Aſſemblies, in which they are very fervent in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to God, with groaning and weeping.—They affirm that they have no Intereſt in the maintaining their Doctrine, ſave only the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion they have of its Truth, and the Zeal of appropriating to the only individual and ſovereign God, the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Glory of his Divinity.—They are confirm'd in their Faith by reading the Word of God, and by the Books which have been written againſt them.—Their Converſation is holy and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Reproach, as far as Men can judg by what they ſee.</q> Much more this impartial Gentleman, none of their Party, ſays to their Praiſe. Even of the Engliſh Unitarians, one of our Reverend Biſhops diſputing againſt them, when he look'd upon them as altogether Socinianiz'd, fairly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes, that he judges they would not think ſo meanly of our Lord Chriſt, but for fear of taking away from the Honour of God Almighty. But I have a Word or two to offer to the Reverend Biſhop of <hi>Sarum,</hi> before I ſpeak of the Engliſh Unitarians of this laſt Age. As ill as he thinks now of theſe Unitarians, I hope he will not retract the noble Character which he once gave of one <hi>George Van Par,</hi> a Dutch-man, burnt in <hi>England</hi> 1549 for Unitarianiſm, which he could not in Conſcience abjure: <q>He led a very exemplary Life for Faſting, Devotion, and a good Converſation, and ſuffer'd with extraordinary Compoſedneſs of Mind.</q> It is out of the way to ſpeak of <hi>Barth. Legat,</hi> [a Man of whoſe vertuous Behaviour the Bookſellers of <hi>Pauls,</hi> among whom he convers'd for 7 Years before his Execution, gave a good account] for he was an <hi>Arian,</hi> burnt <hi>An.</hi> 1611, re-burnt this laſt Year by Mr. <hi>Gailhard:</hi> but it is a better Argument for that poor Man's Seriouſneſs in his Religious Perſwaſion, that he could endure to be burnt for it, than it is for the Sincerity of Mr. <hi>Gailhard,</hi> and the Honour of Calviniſm, that he thirſts after the Blood of thouſands, and damns all Orders and Degrees of Men that do not forward his Executions. But that no ill-minded Perſon may hence take occaſion to ſay, that I inſinuate that the Unitarians are a numerous Body; I openly declare, that whether they are many or few, is more than I know, or care, who am an impartial, tho not always a melancholy By-ſtander: But that they are better Men, truer Chriſtians, and more faithful Subjects, than the revengeful Calviniſts, will appear to any Man that examines the Writings of both ſides. I now come to ſpeak of thoſe Perſons of this laſt Age who have been diſtinguiſh'd by the Name of Unitarians.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anthony Wood,</hi> in his <hi>Athenae Oxonienſes,</hi> 2d Vol. p. 197-199. gives a large Account of <hi>John Bidle,</hi> and ſays among other very commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52170:10"/>
things, that being Maſter of <hi>Crifts School</hi> in <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> 
               <q>He was much eſteem'd for Diligence in his Profeſſion, Severity of Manners, and Sanctity of Life.</q> And when he came to converſe in <hi>London,</hi> after many Years Impriſonment, <q>He was very taking for his Religious Diſcourſe and Saint-like Converſation.</q> Now Mr. <hi>Wood,</hi> I preſume, cannot be ſuſpected of Partiality in favour of an Unitarian. <hi>John Bidle</hi> ſeal'd the Sincerity of his religious Perſwaſion, by his Death; for he took that Sickneſs in <hi>Newgate,</hi> whereof he died 2 days after Removal.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Cooper</hi> ſucceeded Mr. <hi>Bidle</hi> Maſter of <hi>Crifts School</hi> in <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward Miniſter of <hi>Chelthenam</hi> in <hi>Gloceſterſhire;</hi> and after the Act of Uniformity, Miniſter of an Unitarian Congregation in that Place. We ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to all that knew him, whether he was not a Man always compos'd and grave, but of a moſt ſweet and obliging Temper and Converſation. He ſuffer'd thoſe Abuſes from intemperate and riotous Men, when the Nation was running mad they knew not for what, that it broke his Health, and haſtned his End. His Daughter <hi>Mary</hi> died about a Year and a half ſince, a known Unitarian; ſo that the Miniſter who preach'd her Funeral Sermon commended her to his Auditors for a Pattern of Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Vertues, however erroneous in her Judgment. Mr. <hi>Cooper</hi> was ſucceeded in the Guidance of an Unitarian Congregation by <hi>Ralph Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, Henry Sturmy, Thomas Macock,</hi> and <hi>Allen Kear,</hi> all of them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſerious and diligent in their way, devout and pious, ſtrictly honeſt, and charitable to their power; however not ſo accompliſh'd in Humane Learning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Knowles</hi> of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> by long and diligent Study, became very knowing in the Critical Learning of the Scriptures; his much Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Thoughtfulneſs, won him to Unitarianiſm, having in his younger Years been an Independent. His ſingular Piety and Vertue were exemplarily conſpicuous in divers Stations and Stages of his Life. His Labours were directed to the Benefit of others; the greateſt Fruit of them to himſelf, was Dangers and hard Uſages. His Patience was tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by undeſerved Injuries, and Impriſonment even in the time of the raging Plague. Dying, he bequeath'd ſome Books of value to the Library at <hi>Gloceſter;</hi> and a Third of all he had, for the Relief of Men perſecuted for Religion, and other Charities. He alſo was an Unitarian Teacher while he liv'd in <hi>London:</hi> After the Year of the Plague, he convers'd frequently among the Clergy; his Learning, and Seriouſneſs in Religion, was well known among them, of whom ſeveral are now living.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:52170:10"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Gilbert Clerk</hi> was Fellow of <hi>Sidney</hi> College in <hi>Cambridg;</hi> which Place he was oblig'd to leave for Conſcience ſake: after that, he liv'd long at <hi>Stamford,</hi> well known and eſteem'd by Dr. <hi>Cumberland</hi> the Reverend Biſhop of <hi>Peterborough,</hi> who us'd to ſpeak of him by the Name of <hi>Honest Gilbert.</hi> He was Author of two of thoſe Tracts call'd <hi>Tractatus tres,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Noual,</hi> late Rector of <hi>Tydds St. Giles</hi> near <hi>Wisbich</hi> in the <hi>Iſle of Ely,</hi> was a Man of ſingular Piety, and winning Converſation. His Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings teſtify his excellent Learning. He was complain'd of to his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Dioceſan, for omitting thoſe parts of the Liturgy, which after ſome Years of Study and Conſideration he came to be perſwaded againſt. We appeal to the Reverend Biſhop, and even to all the Clergy of <hi>Ely,</hi> eſpecially to him that preached his Funeral Sermon laſt <hi>Trinity Sunday,</hi> whether he deſerv'd not the Character giv'n him.</p>
            <p>I ought not to conclude the Account which I give concerning the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the Unitarians, without taking notice of Mr. <hi>Thomas Firmin.</hi> I have known him intimately theſe 6 or 7 Years, and do now mourn the Loſs of the beſt Man I ever knew: but upon the ſtrength of ſo ſhort an Acquaintance, had I never ſo great Abilities, I ought not to pretend to draw his juſt and full Character: let the Reader expect that, as I do, from one of his deareſt eldeſt Friends. Yet ſomething I am prompted to offer, not only by my Gratitude to his Memory, but in proper Juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice to the Argument before me.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Thomas Firmin</hi> is now gone to his Reſt, but has left behind him a good Name, a Name entertain'd with the higheſt Eſteem among the greateſt and beſt Men, not of our Nation only, but of far diſtant Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries; for it pleas'd God to inſpire him with a wonderful meaſure of true Chriſtian Charity, ſo that he look'd upon himſelf as oblig'd to ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and labour no leſs a Work, than the Good of Mankind in general. One while he was buſy in providing for the Poor, both at home and abroad, as far as his wide and honourable Friendſhips, his own honeſt Acquiſitions, his apprehenſive Underſtanding, conſtant Induſtry, and Application could carry him. In providing for the Poor, his Charity was regular and prudent; he conſider'd what was fitting to be allow'd to the Unhappy, reduc'd by ſome common Caſualty of Providence, and what was neceſſary for the Support of the Sick and the Aged, of lame Perſons, and Children. As for poor People, able to work, he rightly judg'd, the beſt Charity was to find them Work; he did it for thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands: And till the Great Council of the Nation ſhall make effectual Proviſions in this weighty matter, thouſands will be ſadly ſenſible of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52170:11"/>
Loſs of Mr. <hi>Thomas Firmin.</hi> At another time he join'd his Counſels and Intereſt to advance the Trade of <hi>England;</hi> and to whatever good Work he join'd his hand (which he did to many) the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded much more ſucceſsfully through his hearty and active Concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. On all Occaſions he was ready, and ſincere in diſcountenancing Deiſm: for tho he was perſwaded there might be Deiſts, that were ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and good Men, upon the ſole Belief of the Exiſtence of God, and the Expectance of future Recompences; yet he thought Deiſm nothing ſo ſure a Foundation of true Vertue and Goodneſs, as the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-Revelation. He made himſelf one in the Society for Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Manners; and no good Man of that number was more zealouſly affected, by wiſe and legal Methods to ſuppreſs Profaneneſs and Irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which, he well knew, looſen'd the Bands of all Society, and made Man to Man a more dangerous Enemy than biting Serpents, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring Brutes. In ſhort, as to matters Civil, his chief Aim was, the Proſperity of <hi>Old England:</hi> With reſpect to Religion, his ardent De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire was, firſt to convince the World that Natural and Reveal'd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion both, oblig'd them to be morally honeſt; and then to promote univerſal Love and Good-will among Men morally honeſt, however about ſpeculative Doctrines differently perſwaded. But God never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulg'd it, no not to his dearly beloved Son, to go about doing Good, and incur no Envy; to ſhine conſpicuouſly in his Generation with the Splendour of good Works, and meet no Hatred nor Oppoſition. That which Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> met with, proceeded ſometimes from the Jealouſies and Fears of Eccleſiaſticks, eminent for their Honours, Learning, and Piety; but I leave it to the World to judg whether their Jealouſies and Fears, or his Conduct was moſt to blame. But what was Jealouſy and Fear only in the Minds of ſome eminent Eccleſiaſticks, was Paſſion and raſh Zeal, and the over-boiling of an unchriſtian Breaſt in others of a lower form, which I will not ſay but their weaker Judgments might look upon as a piece of good Service to God, and it is not impoſſible for them to have ſuppos'd it the readieſt way to ſerve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. But had Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> been the Heretick which they repreſented him, it would not have misbecome them to have bated him ſome ill Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage for the ſake of his truly Chriſtian Converſation. For wiſe Men will always ſet a greater Value upon a good Life than a clear-ſighted Underſtanding, and never confute a ſuppos'd Hereſy (which does not engage its Profeſſors in immoral Practices) with penal Inflictions in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of convincing Reaſon.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:52170:11"/>
            <p>I will not here diſſemble what I have once heard from Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi>'s own Mouth; <hi>viz.</hi> That a venerable Prelate, or two, had lately charg'd him as a Promoter of Deiſm, which, they ſaid, was the Road to Atheiſm. At this Charge the good Man was extreamly concerned; not that he admitted the Charge, or the Aggravation of it, to be true, (for he was throughly ſatisfied at whoſe doers that Guilt lay) but concern'd he was, that he ſhould be ſo unhappy, as to be in ſuch manner miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged by Perſons of their Worth and Character: whereupon he was more frequent in his Advices to his Friends, that they would be diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly careful of their Converſation, that they would ſhun the Company [as much as their lawful worldly Buſineſs permitted] of immoral Men, but eſpecially of them who queſtion'd the Truth of the Chriſtian Revelation. He thought indeed better of a moral Deiſt than of a wicked Man profeſſing Chriſtianity; yet no one ever talk'd doubtingly of the Chriſtian Revelation in his Company, but was ſure of a juſt and publick Reproof. I could add more to his Praiſe on this Topick, but I hope to ſee it done by one much longer and better acquainted with him than my ſelf. I think Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> ought not to have been look'd upon with an evil eye by any of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> I am ſure the moral Diſcourſes of the moſt learned and pious of the Clergy in his time, differ not at all from his Sentiments, but reſt on the ſame Foundations which he built upon; <hi>viz.</hi> the Foundations of natural Reaſon, and conſonant Chriſtian Revelation. 'Tis true, he did differ from them as they differ from one another, in ſome ſpeculative Opinions; and I will ſay that for both their Honours, wherein the Clergy differ'd among themſelves, each Party thought Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> in the more pardonable Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror: ſo that if Hereſy had been doom'd to the Fire, the Church would have been almoſt half deſtroyed before it had come to his turn.</p>
            <p>'Twere too invidious a thing to name either thoſe that eſteem'd, or thoſe that malign'd him; but might I have the liberty which ſome Philoſophick Fathers, after their Converſion from Paganiſm, made bold with, I would adventure at a Pathetick Argument, and by a proper <hi>Proſopopoeia</hi> introduce Mr. <hi>Grigg,</hi> Dr. <hi>Whichcot,</hi> or Archbiſhop <hi>Tillotſon,</hi> vindicating the Honour of their dear Friend. Had they been now living, they would have done it effectually. I am conſcious I cannot put into their mouths Words worthy them or him; but the leaſt they would have ſaid, muſt have imported thus much—He expoſes his own Judgment, who accuſes Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> of Hereſy; he proclaims himſelf an ill Man, who queſtions his Morals.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:52170:12"/>
            <p>Againſt his worſt Enemies, thoſe that could take Offence at nothing but the Vertue and Reputation of the Man, I ſhall not inveigh ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: it is enough to ſay, the <hi>Coffee-man</hi> can have no Comfort in his Scandal, which no body will credit: and as for Mr. <hi>Burgeſs,</hi> he took it up, not from any manner of Probability, [even his own Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſeveral others, told him it was a horrid Calumny] but out of pure Zeal againſt what he calls <hi>Socinianiſm,</hi> becauſe he knows no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. It was this which made him talk, in his fanciful way, about ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Goats, and ſweet-ſcented Panthers, painted Snakes, and immoral Poiſon. But, whether it pleaſes him or not, the injur'd Man's fair Fame has taken Wing, and is not to be bounded within our narrow Seas, or blaſted by his envious Metaphors. The Maſters of Oratory ſay, thoſe Metaphors ought to be ſhunn'd which are borrow'd <hi>à re turpi, aut ſordidâ;</hi> and thoſe which are too far fetch'd, had better have been let alone: but if a Man is above theſe Rules, then with his Goats, Snakes, and Panthers, he may make what work he pleaſes; and if he be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, at one bold Stroke to defy all Rules, and ridicule his own Diſcourſe, let him repreſent the ſerious Buſineſs of reproving Sin, by ſnuffing a Candle.</p>
            <p>By accident, our Enemies often happen to do us greater Kindneſs than our Friends. So happen'd it to Mr. <hi>Firmin;</hi> All that convers'd with him were extreamly taken with the ſoft, agreeable, and endearing Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of the Man; but what a Friend ſays in ſuch a caſe, is often ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to have more of Affection than Truth in it: but Providence, to ſecure the Fame of Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> mov'd an Enemy to bear Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to his Honour; for one that with a malevolent eye obſerv'd him, repreſents him as a Man of <hi>Socinus</hi>'s Make, complaiſant and ſweet even to ſuch as oppoſe and deteſt his Hereſy. Now I know of no He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy which he had; I am ſure he did not take the Opinions of <hi>Socinus</hi> upon content, but agreed with, or differ'd from, that Writer, as he ſaw cauſe: if he had any thing in him bordering upon Hereſy, it was his Obſtinateneſs in believing with his own Underſtanding thoſe things only which appear'd to him credible, agreeable to Holy Scripture, and not contradictory to Natural Reaſon: but his Converſation indeed, that (as his Enemy ſays) was always complaiſant and ſweet; for, alas! he was bred a Chriſtian, and never us'd to return Railing for Railing. But by the way, if a ſweet good Nature be an Heretical Temper, then a furious ill Nature muſt be an orthodox Temper, and then this Term of Art, <hi>Orthodox,</hi> will at laſt become but ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Word for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:52170:12"/>
            <p>Who would have imagin'd that the Wit of an Enemy ſhould have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd againſt Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> ſuch an Objection, as that <hi>He was open-hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Poor with his own or other Folks Money?</hi> Both parts of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction are true; but to ſuppoſe only the latter ſo, that proves that Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> was well known for a faithful and prudent Diſpenſer of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: and to ſuppoſe he had nothing of his own to give, which is ſpitefully inſinuated; yet even this redounds to his Honour, for is it not a very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable thing, if there were no more in't, for a Man to ſpend ſo much of his time upon the Poor? I am apt to think it was offence taken at the ill Lives of the Chriſtians, rather than the Doctrines of Chriſtianity, which made the renown'd <hi>Averroes</hi> wiſh, that his Soul might reſt with the Philoſophers: now have I that awful regard for the Vertue and Piety of Mr. <hi>Firmin;</hi> that let his Adverſaries revile him, and call him Heretick as long as they pleaſe, I cannot forbear praying, may my Soul reſt with this thrice excellent and truly Chriſtian Unitarian.</p>
            <p>It is to ſpare the Reader's farther trouble, that I deduce no longer a Catalogue of Engliſh Unitarians, not long ſince deceas'd, who were neither Atheiſts, nor Deiſts, nor Profane, nor immoral Perſons, (as is the Cry of ſome now when they have ſpent all their fair Arguments, and diſtruſt their Efficacy) but ſeriouſly religious, fully ſatisfied of the truth of the Chriſtian Revelation, devout, honeſt, and charitable.</p>
            <p>If it objected that the Unitarians lately deceas'd, whom I have now character'd, ſeparated themſelves from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and form'd religious Aſſemblies to themſelves apart; and therefore the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians now living cannot pretend to the Title of Orthodox Churchmen. I reply, 1. That as for the Unitarians deceas'd, it is probable to me, that they ſeparated [after ſuch manner as they did ſeparate, which how far it was, I have not been made acquainted] that they might not ſeem to profeſs a Tritheiſtick Trinity, compos'd of three diſtinct Infinite Minds and Subſtances; for in their time our eminent Eccleſiaſticks had not ſo particularly explain'd themſelves againſt that heatheniſh Notion. 2. There may be a conſcientious Separation from the Church by Men that agree with her in Doctrinals: ſuch I take the Separation of the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, Independents, and Anabaptiſts to be. 3. The Unitarians now living being lately ſatisfied that the Majority of the Doctors of the Church, do not mean by their ſcolaſtick Terms ſtill retain'd, any ſuch Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity as is plain Tritheiſm, but ſuch a Nominal Trinity as the Biſhop of <hi>Sarum</hi> and Dr. <hi>S—th</hi> have explain'd, and as the Learned Biſhop of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> has ſpoke of, tho a little obſcurely, which learned Men cannot help; and having therefore publickly profeſs'd their Agreement with the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52170:13"/>
Church of <hi>England</hi> on this and other diſputed Articles, I ought not in reaſon but to look upon them as ſound and orthodox Members of the Church of <hi>England</hi> as to their Faith.</p>
            <p>If it be <hi>ſtill</hi> objected, That there is in ſome of the firſt Prints of theſe Unitarians ſomething very like a formal Oppoſition of the Articles of the Church: let it be conſider'd they have of late anſwer'd for themſelves, confeſſing that careleſs or leſs accurate Expreſſions may have been us'd by both Parties, of which neither ought to take advantage, becauſe (which is originally a Tritheiſt's Argument, but the Nominaliſts acquieſce in't) there is no Heterodox Intention on either ſide: Nay, the Unitarians have deſir'd, that thoſe Paſſages in their Writings, (which might be wreſted by an ill-natur'd Adverſary to their Diſadvantage) be interpreted accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their later more accurate and careful explaining their Minds.</p>
            <p>If it be farther urg'd (by thoſe that love no Satisfaction, but the Ruin of poor Men who have had the Misfortune to diſpleaſe them) that it is an intolerable Shame for the Unitarians to ſhift about thus, after they have made a hurly-burly in the Chutch; they may perhaps deſire to know whether they are more to blame than the Realiſts, and whether they may not have as free leave to explain their firſt Writings, as the Realiſts to explain their firſt? For Dr. <hi>S—th</hi> was not angry at the Dean for explaining his obnoxious Tritheiſtick Phraſes, but becauſe his Explanation was as arrant Tritheiſm, as his firſt obnoxious Tritheiſtick Phraſes: which cannot be ſaid of the Unitarians in that Book where they have declar'd their Agreement with the Catholick Church. Whereupon even Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> cries out, <q>Why ſhould I contend with theſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick and Orthodox Men? Who will fall out with thoſe that profeſs agreement with the Catholick Church?</q> Indeed he does not uſe theſe friendly Words, till the very latter end of the very worſt Book he ever wrote. It's true, he acknowledg'd himſelf in debt to the Civility of the nameleſs Socinian, [ſo he calls him, for he calls no Man he diſlikes by a right Name] and promis'd a return of Civility about ſix Leaves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but it ſeems he had not quite diſcharg'd his Stomach of the foul Matter which lay upon it, and could not ſpeak him fair, till he had call'd him all the names he could think on: juſt his way of dealing with Mr. <hi>Bold,</hi> for ſeven or eight Leaves together he repreſents him as a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verter of the Foundations of Chriſtianity, a Worſhipper of the Idol that Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> and Mr. <hi>Lock</hi> have ſet up; a dull, phlegmatick, horrid lying Fellow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in the cloſe he is ready, [if what he ſays is true] to expreſs the deference which he ows to Mr. <hi>Bold</hi>'s Perſon and Office. From whence, tho it does not follow but that Mr. <hi>Bold</hi> may be a learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52170:13"/>
and honeſt Man, (for all that Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſays is not Goſpel) yet it does plainly follow, that Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> thinks he ows a deference to an Antichriſtian, Idolatrous, dull, horrid lying Fellow, and that he is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to expreſs the ſame; and by joining Mr. <hi>Bold</hi>'s Perſon, [whom he repreſents as an Antichriſtian, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] he fairly implies that it is his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, that the Office ſanctifies the Perſon, tho the Perſon be an Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, Idolatrous, dull, horrid lying Fellow. I hope without offence to any ſober Man, it may be ſet down as an inſtance of Prieſtcraft, this ſubtle Contrivance, That the holy Office of the ſpiritual Man ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piate whatever is done amiſs by the Sinner: I word it gently, and don't purſue it ſo far as the matter leads. I have ſaid what I had to ſay con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Perſons of the late Deceas'd, and now living Unitarians; and as far as I perceive, the Men are honeſt, their Converſation blameleſs, the Holy Scripture is their Rule, and they interpret it according to the beſt of their underſtanding; nay, as good luck will have it, they interpret it juſt as the founder and major part of the Church does, and have always ſo interpreted it, tho they did not always perceive the Agreement between the Church and themſelves: they are not as they have been odiouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil'd, Men of no ſeriouſneſs in Religion, meer Deiſts, much leſs Atheiſts, or (as a Reverend Father out of the abundance of his Charity compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments them) irreligious profligate Villains; but it is to be hop'd that he will recal thoſe bitter words, at leaſt for his own ſake; for I am told they are reſolv'd to make it plainly appear to the World, that his Lordſhip's Doctrine in ſome of his Books [and in ſome perhaps not] accords as much with the Racovian Catechiſm, as theirs: ſo that if there be not two Rules to judg of Hereſy, one Fire will ſerve them and his Lordſhip both.</p>
            <p>I come now to conſider what is the Tendency of the Unitarian Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines: only one Queſtion I have to premiſe. Suppoſing that the Converſation of theſe Men is ſuch as becomes the Goſpel [which from my Soul I believe] but their Doctrines falſe, and of miſchievous Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency; would it not have become their jealous Adverſaries [who by the Rules of the Goſpel are oblig'd to believe the beſt which a Cauſe will bear] to have look'd upon them as Men erring through Ignorance, and not perceiving the miſchievous Tendency of their Doctrines? A good Man cannot promote a Doctrine which he knows to be falſe, or of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous Conſequence; but a zealous or a proud Man is capable of ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting a Doctrine to be falſe, and of miſchievous Conſequence, which is nothing ſo.</p>
            <p>Two ways the Unitarians defend their Doctrines from the Imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of miſchievous Conſequence or Tendency; 1. By ingenuouſly, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52170:14"/>
and largely explaining their Minds on thoſe Articles which they were charg'd to deny, or expound amiſs. 2. By making it appear, that they have no particular private Opinions about Matters commonly held neceſſary to Salvation, different from the Church of <hi>England;</hi> i. e. if the Biſhops and chief Doctors of the Church know what the Church means.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By ingenuouſly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Writer who drew up the Trinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Scheme, quotes not the Authors whence he drew it, I ſuppoſe, becauſe his Deſign was to reprove the Errors of Men, and ſpare their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> who knows not when his Friends are well us'd, tells him, he had no <hi>credible</hi> Authors to vouch that Scheme: Sure he meant <hi>creditable.</hi> But 'tis no new thing for Men of buſtling Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to forget their Mother-tongue. The Unitarian will not pretend to find credible Authors, <hi>i. e.</hi> Authors fit to be truſted, for the Scheme which he looks upon as erroneous; they may be credible in Matters of fact, in Matters of Faith not ſo. Matters of Faith are not to be taken on the bare Credit of any Man's word: but if creditable, <hi>i. e.</hi> Authors of eſteem, to vouch that Scheme, will content Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> he may have them in due time; and to be very civil to him, he ſhall be one.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> fram'd a Socinian Creed, and quoted his Authors for every Article: a Unitarian Writer replied, but ſays Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> 
               <q>That Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman in effect acknowledges that the Articles I fixt on the Socinians are the very Doctrines and Sentiments of thoſe Perſons, worded as I ſet them down; and that the Authors whom I quoted deliver'd them in thoſe very Terms, and that I have not miſrepreſented any of them.</q> He that will may truſt Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> but I for my part deſire to be excus'd; for the Unitarian Writer in his <hi>Agreement of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians with the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church,</hi> does expreſly affirm, <q>That he has examin'd ſome of Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi>'s principal References, and can ſay of them, that they are either Perverſions, or downright Falſifications, of what the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors (referred to) did intend.</q> It is true, he has alledg'd no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; but he ſeldom is long, on ſuch an occaſion, in a Friend's Debt. But on every Article of Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi>'s Socinian Creed, he has ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, accurately, and amply declar'd, what it is which the Engliſh Unitarians do believe; to all which Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> returns only this Cenſure—It is Higgling, or Dodging, or Recantation. Now if an ingenuous, accurate, and ample declaring what the Engliſh Unitarians do believe, be higgling, and dodging, who can help it? If it be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantation, methinks Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſhould have rejoic'd, that his Labours had contributed to win Souls to the true Faith. But, alas! he is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:52170:14"/>
afraid that it is a real Recantation, and therefore he beſlaves the Party; for he was in hopes they would have perſiſted in their Error, that he might have had the Pleaſure of ſeeing them burn'd, and the Comfort of believing them damn'd. But notwithſtanding this his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Unitarians ſtand upon it, that neither are their Doctrines erroneous, not have they forſaken them. No! why, ſays Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> 
               <q>This Anonymous Scribe, meerly to avoid the Imputation of ſome Articles I faſtned on the <hi>Socinians,</hi> ventures to renounce what the Staunch-men of that Party have aſſerted.</q> Well! but if he never did aſſert what the Staunch-men have aſſerted, nor ever profeſs himſelf a Diſciple of <hi>Socinus,</hi> may he not have leave to renounce that which is falſly laid to the Charge of himſelf and his Friends? I doubt not but Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> knows what's Hereſy enough to burn a Man; but does he think to perſwade the Unitarians, as they do Witches in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to confeſs the Crime whereof they are not guilty, that ſo he may have the Satisfaction to glut his vengeful Eyes with the Flames in which they fry? But Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> would fain prove that the Anonymous Scribe [as he calls him, for he's full of his Nicknames] <q>has alſo renounc'd what the modern domeſtick Socinians have aſſerted.</q> He offers this Inſtance for Proof. The Anonymous Scribe had ſaid, <q>He may for our parts be Anathema, that teaches or believes that Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, <hi>viz.</hi> That there is no Merit in what Chriſt did or ſuffer'd, and that he made not Satisfaction for our Sins.</q> And yet in one of their Prints they let us know, <q>That the Oblation which Chriſt made of himſelf, was not made to the Juſtice of God, or by way of Repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> but, as all other Sacrifices, by way of humble Suit.</q> How theſe two Paſſages do directly contradict one another, Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> when he is at leiſure, will inform us: In the mean time, I make bold to acquaint him, that before I have done, I will produce him an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Cloud of Witneſſes of the laſt and of this preſent Age, eminent Doctors and Biſhops of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> offering the ſame Senſe for Orthodox, which Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> decries as groſs Socinianiſm. Mr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> having offer'd nothing elſe excepting bad Language, againſt tho Book call'd—<hi>Agreement of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians with the Catholick Church,</hi> thither I refer the Reader; for, not Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> himſelf (I preſume) tho he's a bold Man, will dare to pronounce the Doctrines which the Unitarians there own, to be falſe and of miſchievous Tendency.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> and ſome others have one invidious Objection which I do not remember particularly anſwer'd: They ſay Socinianiſm is the Road to Deiſm, and Deiſm the Road to Atheiſm. Now if this were true,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52170:15"/>
it does not affect the Unitarians, who are neither Atheiſts, nor meer Deiſts, nor yet Socinians. But Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> takes every of theſe Poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for indubitate — A Unitarian is a Socinian; Socinianiſm tends to Deiſm; Deiſm, to Atheiſm. Theſe things, with him, neceſſarily hang together, like a <hi>Hobbian</hi> Chain of Thoughts. Yet I will ſhew him how looſe the Links of this Chain are; if he knows how, let him faſten them. That a Unitarian is no Socinian, appears plain from the <hi>Agreement,</hi> to which I hope to add ſome farther Proof: that Socinianiſm does not tend to Deiſm, I will now offer ſome Reaſon; but Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> muſt take it for an <hi>Auctarium,</hi> which I need not throw him in, but ſhall do it out of pure Charity, to convince him of his adventurous Bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at Calumny, and extream Shortneſs at Argument. By Deiſm (I take it) is commonly meant, Natural Religion, founded on the Belief of the Exiſtence of a God, and of a future Life, with a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection and Disbelief of all Revelation. Socinianiſm is not the Road to this Deiſm. I know not of any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Catechiſm which accounts for the Truth of the Chriſtian Revelation, except the <hi>Racovian.</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks it is a Deficiency; and if Deiſm does abound ſo much, as Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſays, ſurely 'twere not amiſs, that our Youth, and other docile, apprehenſive (tho not Book-learn'd) People ſhould be infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, in a plain Catechetical way, how the Authority of the Old and New Teſtament is to be prov'd: This may be learn'd in that Catechiſm of the Socinians which is call'd the <hi>Racovian;</hi> the firſt Chapter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of near eight Leaves, proving that we have no juſt Grounds to doubt, but ſufficient Reaſons to perſwade us to give Credence to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures. Now the Arguments there us'd are not trivial <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or weak; are not ſuch as might give an Adverſary occaſion to object that they mean to betray the Cauſe. Let Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> tell me what can be ſaid more to the purpoſe, or better, in ſuch a compaſs; touching the Sufficiency, Chap. 2. touching the Clearneſs of Holy Scriptures, Chap. 3. The So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians have declar'd themſelves ſo plainly, ſo judiciouſly, ſo Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxly, that their imbitter'd Adverſaries have nothing to find fault with. Now ſuppoſing that theſe Men were widely miſtaken about the Senſe of ſeveral difficult Texts, yet who, that had any Modeſty left, would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them of inclining to Deiſm, of rejecting the Authority of Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and denying the Truth of the Chriſtian Religion? Let Mr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> defend the Chriſtian Religion, if he can, better than the Socinians have defended it; but if he has no ſtronger Arguments than they have us'd for that purpoſe, why would he have them ſuſpected of Deiſm? To labour to perſwade People that the Socinians, who have ſaid ſo much
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52170:15"/>
to eſtabliſh the divine Authority of the Bible, do not themſelves believe it, is, methinks, no other, than to tempt Scepticks to conclude, that enough cannot be ſaid to eſtabliſh their Authority; which Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> of all Men ought not to do, unleſs he himſelf be a meer Deiſt; which Imputation, as yet, I forbear to lay to his Charge, tho in truth, by his laſt Book [which he calls <hi>A Vindication of Fundamental Articles,</hi> &amp;c. but might better have entitled it, <hi>A Vindication of Railing,</hi> (ſee p. 26, 27.) which Title, the Book fully anſwers, for it is one interrupted <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] it does not appear that he is a Chriſtian. Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> had a Secretary, who when he retir'd to <hi>Tihalds,</hi> his Country Seat, was wont to lay aſide his Cognizances of Honour, with theſe words, <hi>Lie there Lord Burleigh;</hi> and then the grave Stateſman would be very merry and gameſome. It take Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> to have much of that honourable Gentleman's Humour, for I cannot imagine that he has utterly renounc'd Chriſtianity; only perhaps when he writes or preaches Controverſy, he cries, <hi>Lie by for a while, lie by ſo long good Chriſtian;</hi> but the angry Story once finiſh'd, or the Sermon over, he's the ſame Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> as learned, as honeſt, and as pious as he was before. I beg my Reader always to conſider, that I defend Socinianiſm only <hi>quo ad hoc,</hi> it is not the Road to meer Deiſm: in the next place, I will prove that meer Deiſm is not the Road to Atheiſm, Deiſm, I defin'd to be Natural Religion founded on the Belief of the Exiſtence of a God, and of a future Life. There may, for ought I know, be Men who would be counted Deiſts, that believe not a jot of the Life to come, but theſe, I judg, if they were put to't, would hardly be able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh themſelves from downright Atheiſts. To me it is all one, to queſtion the Exiſtence of a God, and to queſtion his future Retributions; but Natural Religion, which depends on the Belief that God is, and that he is a Rewarder, cannot be the Road to Atheiſm. I will not deny but that Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> knows the Road to Atheiſm as well as any Man breathing, but he muſt not put it upon us, that Deiſm is that Road; he may as well bear us in hand, that ſailing Eaſtward is the Road to the <hi>West-Indies.</hi> There cannot be a plainer Contradiction, than to ſay, That the Belief of a God leads to the Belief of none. Were Atheiſm the prevailing Opinion I grant to Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> we ſhould quickly ſee it move apace to the Ruin and Subverſion of Kingdoms and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, Societies and Bodies Politick; but upon the Principles of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm, <hi>i. e.</hi> on the Foundation of Natural Religion, publick Peace and Order ſtood firm before the days of the Chriſtian Revelation: and did it not do ſo among the neighbour Nations that hated the Jews? Among
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52170:16"/>
the Deiſts, during the flouriſhing days of the growing Greatneſs of the <hi>Romans,</hi> there were, I believe, as few Atheiſts as there are among Chriſtians now.</p>
            <p>Let no malicious Adverſary here pretend, that I plead the Cauſe of Deiſm; no, I do not: this I do, I maintain that Deiſm is not the Road to Atheiſm, as ſome Men very weakly and imprudently have affirm'd; for it rather is the Road to Chriſtianity. I know Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> will be angry with me for what I am going to tell him; but let him ſummon all the Powers and Skill he has in Logick, ſeaſoning it with a doſe of ill Nature <hi>quantum ſufficit,</hi> and then refute me if he can. I here affirm, That if the Man who is not yet a Chriſtian, be an honeſt, moral Deiſt, a Believer in God, and an Expecter of a future Judgment, he is, at leaſt <hi>in precinctu ad ſalutem,</hi> and ſtands fair to be a Chriſtian; no reveal'd Religion offers ſo reaſonable Grounds to win him as the Chriſtian. Now I much wonder that ſo ingenuous and moderate a Man as Mr. <hi>Norris</hi> ſhould join with Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> in ſo ignorant, invidious, and deſigning an Aſſertion as this, <hi>viz.</hi> Deiſm is the Road to Atheiſm. Mr. <hi>Norris</hi>'s elegant way of wording it is, <q>He that is once a Deiſt, is in a hopeful way of being an Atheiſt whenever he pleaſes.</q> No, Mr. <hi>Norris,</hi> no; an honeſt moral Deiſt's Principles are directly pointed againſt Atheiſm: but a ſpiteful, proud, and cruel Chriſtian, is in very great danger of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Atheiſt, if he be not one already. But perhaps Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> may reply, he ſpake not of a Deiſt, who never had been a Chriſtian, but that his meaning was, The Man who falls from Chriſtianity to Deiſm is in the Road to be an Atheiſt. To this I reply, That tho the Unitarians are firmly perſwaded of the Truth of the Chriſtian Religion, yet they need not grant the Aſſertion thus explain'd to be true; for, what Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tianity teaches, beyond that which natural Reaſon dictates, has not the Efficacy to prevent Atheiſm, which natural Reaſon has: however, I am content, and I think the Unitarians ought to be ſo likewiſe, That the Man who is afraid of a Bullet ſhould wear a Coat of Mail, as well as keep out of Gun-ſhot.</p>
            <p>I hope the Reader now plainly ſees, that there is never a Link of Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi>'s Chain that will hold. The Unitarians are Orthodox [of which more anon.] The Socinians are ſo far Orthodox, that they are firmly perſwaded of the Verity of the Chriſtian Religion, and are not meer Deiſts: Conſcientious moral Deiſts are in no danger of being Atheiſts. But is there no dangerous Road leading to Atheiſm, of which Men ought to be warn'd, that they come not near it? Yes, there is; and it is a wide Road too, pav'd all along with raſh Cenſures, ill Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52170:16"/>
falſe Stories, barbarous unchriſtian Dealing, forg'd Decrees of inconditional Reprobation, and Stoical Fate, this is the Road, and the Perſecutor, the Slanderer, and the Calviniſt drive hard, like ſo many <hi>Jehu</hi>'s in it, leaving Deiſm a long way off on the right hand. The Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Religion does not allow its Profeſſors to be ſo much as proper Judges of Hereſy as commonly underſtood, much leſs to be Executioners of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks; for the reaſon given why the Tales ſhould not be pull'd up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Harveſt, is, leſt ſome good Corn ſhould be pull'd up with it. The Chriſtian Religion directs Men by fair Carriage, by the Words of Truth and Soberneſs; to convince them whom we think in the wrong. He that is cruel, abuſive and unjuſt, can be a Chriſtian only in name; in reality he is Infidel all over. Then for Calviniſm, that four Syſtem which is good for nothing but to fight with, [but I hope Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> is inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent from that, for he has ſourneſs enough without it] how ſhould it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than tend to Atheiſm, when it repreſents Man without Free-will, and God without Goodneſs?</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Unitarians defend their Doctrines from the Imputation of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous Conſequence or Tendency, by making it appear that they have no particular private Opinions about matters commonly held neceſſary to Salvation, different from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that is, if the Biſhops and chief Doctors of the Church know what the Church means.</p>
            <p>I do confeſs that I much fear the Unitarians may have private Opinions about Articles commonly held neceſſary to Salvation, different from the Opinions of the Compilers of the 39 Articles, and from the Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical literal Senſe of thoſe Articles; for through them, as alſo through our <hi>Homilies,</hi> there runs a Vein of that Scheme which at this day is call'd Calviniſm. But the Grammatical literal Senſe of our Articles and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies</hi> are fall'n into the hands of Governing Biſhops, Deans, and Doctors, and Governed inferiour Prieſts and Deacons; of whom a vaſt Majority [as appears by their Prints and daily Sermons] expound them very wide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly different from the Grammatical literal Senſe, intended by the firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilers. Words and Phraſes have nothing in their own nature which can fix them to this or that particular Senſe: it is common Conſent and way of ſpeaking which appropriates them, and therefore our Articles and <hi>Homilies</hi> which once held forth ſome of the Predeſtinarian Rigors for the Doctrine of the Church, are not to be ſuppos'd to teach the ſame ſtill, now that the Conſent of our Church runs ſo ſtrongly another way. Poſſibly the Unitarians have not <hi>Cranmer, Latimer</hi> and <hi>Ridly</hi> on their ſide, in the Points now controverted; but in them and all other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Articles, they have the Reverend Biſhops of <hi>Worceſter</hi> and <hi>Sarum,</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:52170:17"/>
Dr. <hi>South,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> with them: indeed if thoſe Biſhops and Doctors ſhould neither be the Church, nor conjoin'd with enough to make a Majority, which muſt be the Church, the Lord have mercy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Unitarians; for who is it that indulges his Brother a due liberty of Conſcience, but when he needs it himſelf? but the Biſhops and Doctors aforeſaid being conjoin'd with an unconteſtable Majority, the Unitarians have nothing more to do, to prove that they have no particular private Opinions about Matters commonly held neceſſary to Salvation, but to ſhew their Agreement with thoſe Biſhops and Doctors; or, which is much the ſame thing, the Agreement of thoſe Biſhops and Doctors with them: now this has been amply and fairly done by an Unitarian, I know not whom, he being a perfect Stranger to me; but it matters not much who he is, whether a Tranſmarine, or Ciſmarine Divine, or no Divine at all, 'tis nothing to the Cauſe that. Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> by drawing up a Creed from Socinian Writers, moſtly Foreigners, and publiſhing it as the Creed of the Unitarians, gave this Unitarian an occaſion to declare the Senſe of himſelf and his Friends upon all thoſe Points, which he has done in a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per call'd, <hi>The Agreement of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians with the Catholick Church.</hi> Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> takes no notice of this ingenuous Declaration; but becauſe the Author has not alſo defended every unſtudied doubtful or extravagant Saying, which this or that Socinian may have publiſh'd, therefore he triumphs, rubs his Forehead, and proclaims, That the Unitarian has not one Syllable to ſay for himſelf, or againſt him. Now in my Judgment, the Unitarian might as well expect that Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſhould defend all the Pagan Tritheiſm which might be quoted from Dr. <hi>Cudworth,</hi> Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Sherlock;</hi> for what has the Unitarian more to do with the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Socinians, than Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> has with theſe learned and real Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians and Tritheiſts? For, the Unitarian does not blindly follow the Socinians, but while he takes up with ſome of their critical Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of difficult Texts, he forſakes them in others; even Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> himſelf agreeing perhaps in moſt points with the aforeſaid Realiſts, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts them for Orthodox Brethren, while he lets them keep their Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm to themſelves: it were a very unfair thing in me, if I ſhould pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the religious Frenzies of Mr. <hi>Gailhard</hi> [which have been ſo well cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis'd by two honeſt Gentlemen] as part of Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi>'s Faith; nay, I much doubt whether he would be content to own all that I could quote him out of the <hi>Origines Eccleſ.</hi> and the <hi>Irenicum</hi> of that Patron of his, whoſe Name [he ſays] is not ſo much the Name of a Perſon, or a Family, as it is the Name of profound Learning, and ſolid Religion. I mention not thoſe Books as if I thought them full of Errors, for I have a greater
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52170:17"/>
eſteem for them than perhaps the Author himſelf may have now, or Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> either: but my meaning is, that neither ſhould Mr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> be put to anſwer for the Tritheiſm of the Realiſts, nor the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians cenſur'd for Socinian Miſtakes. By the way, were I a great Man, and my Fame wanted ſome ſpecious Decoration, I would beſtow my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging Bounty on an Eccleſiaſtick rather than a meer Heatheniſh Poet; not but that the meer Heatheniſh Poet might have the moſt Wit, the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt Fancy, and as little Conſcience as any grave Panegyriſt whatſoever: but becauſe an Eccleſiaſtick for a ſmall matter will ſay all that he can to make a God of his Patron, while the other meaſures his Encomiums by the Number of the Guineas that are paid him. To return, the Socinian Perſwaſion is to be ſeen in the <hi>Racovian</hi> Catechiſm: The Engliſh Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarian Sentiments in the <hi>Agreement,</hi> &amp;c. thoſe their Sentiments there ſet down, no one that I know of has undertaken to refute or charge with Hereſy. But farther, from ſeveral Tracts of the Unitarians it appears that thoſe their Adverſaries who have been diſtinguiſh'd by the Name of Nominals, and who are a conſiderable Majority of the Church, do yet explain the controverted Articles to the very ſame Senſe as do the Unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, I refer the Reader chiefly to the Diſcourſe concerning the <hi>Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and Real Trinitarians,</hi> to which I can add but little; yet ſome Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces I ſhall produce, which make it plain that the Leaders of the Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naliſts in the controverted Points differ as little from the Socinians, as the Unitarians do. The Racovian Catechiſm affirms that the Eſſence of God is but one in number, and that in the Eſſence of God there is but one Perſon: The firſt of the 39 Articles of the Church of <hi>England</hi> teaches, That in the Unity of the Godhead there are three Perſons; this Doctrine the Learned Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi> undertakes to defend, ſuppoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it gainſay'd by the Socinians and by the Unitarians: But if it be gainſay'd by neither, his Lordſhip has thrown away a great deal of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to little purpoſe. 'Tis true, a Man has not the leſs Learning for this ſort of Expence; but then if he ſpends much Labour in it, 'tis an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervaluing of his Judgment. The different Explications which the Racovian Catechiſm and his Lordſhip give of this ambiguous homony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous word, <hi>Perſon,</hi> being conſider'd, it is plain that they differ about the meaning of a word, and that's all, while their Doctrine is one and the ſame. The Racovian Catechiſm defines a Perſon to be an Individual Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Eſſence; but, according to the Bp of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> a Perſon is one and the ſame Nature under different Modes of Subſiſtence.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vindic. of the Trin.</hi> p. 14, 15, 16.</note> The Biſhop will not ſay that there are three Individual Intelligent Eſſences in the Godhead: The <hi>Racovians</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:52170:18"/>
never did ſay, that the Godhead might not be conſider'd as ſubſiſting un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der divers Modes. Now as for the Unitarians in this Particular, their Caſe is this—While they follow'd the Definiture of the Racovians, which was accommodated to the common Acception of the word, <hi>Perſon;</hi> their Doctrine was—But One Perſon in the One God: But when the Nominals unanimouſly declar'd that they meant by <hi>Perſon,</hi> not a compleat Intelligent Being, but only Relations, Properties, or Modes of Subſiſtence; then the Unitarians made no ſcruple to own three Perſons in one Godhead. As to the Particular before us then, all that I would beg of my Lord of <hi>Worceſter</hi> in behalf of the Unitarians, is, that they may have leave to be as much Socinian as his Lordſhip, more they will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire: and if his Lordſhip hath any Arguments to refute the Trinity of the Realiſts conſiſting of three diſtinct Minds, Intelligent Beings, Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which the Socinians have not us'd before him; let him be pleas'd to communicate them, and the Unitarians will promiſe for the future to oppoſe the Tritheiſm of the Realiſts only by his Lordſhip's Arguments, and not by any borrow'd from the Socinians; farther, the Unitarians will be content that his Lordſhip ſhall only declare himſelf againſt the Doctrine of the Realiſts, who are by reaſon of their equal Learning, Eminence and not contemptible Numbers, too conſiderable to be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe griev'd: but far from every Orthodox Father be that Injuſtice, common among Boys, who when the Perſon that gives the Offence is out of their reach, ſtrike him that ſtands next.</p>
            <p>It is not much out of place here to commend the good temper of the Unitarians, who for conſerving brotherly Love and Peace among Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians will not litigate about Terms and Words, on which the Authority that impoſes them puts an honeſt Senſe and Meaning: there are [it muſt not be denied] no ſmall Inconveniences in altering the common ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of words; but that's ſo well remedied by a new Definition of the words that are alter'd, that I would ſooner envy our Church the Power of declaring Articles of Faith, than this Liberty of making words ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify, in ſpite of common Senſe, what they pleaſe. The greateſt Miſchief is, when words that muſt be us'd in Theological Controverſies, muſt not ſignify as they have commonly done, nor yet be determin'd anew to any other expreſs Particular; but this is the Fault of ſome Realiſts. One of the Unitarians in his Book call'd, <hi>The Agreement,</hi> &amp;c. p. 36. has examin'd the Senſe of the Biſhop of <hi>Sarum</hi> concerning the Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Divinity of our Lord Chriſt, and grants that the Senſe of his Lordſhip may paſs for Orthodox, but undeniably evinces that the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Unitarians are a degree or two more Orthodox. I ſhall not
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:52170:18"/>
repeat, but refer the Reader to the place, chuſing rather in purſuit of my chief purpoſe to inſiſt wholly on this, that there is not ſo wide a Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between his Lordſhip's Explanations and the Racovian Catechiſm as might be imagin'd, and that his Lordſhip is at leaſt as much Racovian as the Unitarians. I do not aim to vindicate all that's in the Racovian Catechiſm, but only ſo much of it as the Unitarians are concern'd with. The Racovian Catechiſm teaches that Jeſus Chriſt was a true Man by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but had not truly a Divine Nature; that Jeſus Chriſt was not ſo conſtituted of a Divine and Human Nature, as a Man is of a Body and Soul. The Biſhop of <hi>Sarum</hi> teaches in the 2d of his four Treatiſes, <hi>p.</hi> 96. That the Godhead by the Eternal Word, the 2d in the bleſſed Three, dwelt in, and was ſo inwardly united to the human Nature of Jeſus Chriſt, that by virtue of it God and Man were truly one Perſon, as our Soul and Body make one Man. It muſt be confeſs'd that here is Contradiction in Terms direct and plain as can be: but let the Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the Terms which is given on either ſide be duly weigh'd, and it will evidently appear, that the Racovians and the Biſhop agree very well as to the Subſtance of the Article, except in one ſmall reſpect wherein his Lordſhip is at ſome ſmall variance with himſelf. When the Racovians teach that our Lord Chriſt who was a true Man, had not a true Divine Nature, they do not mean that he was not conſtantly illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, conducted, and actuated by the Godhead; but only that the Godhead did not become commenſurate to a finite Man, ſo as to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a real Communication of Idioms, and thereby make the great things which are ſpoken of Chriſt in reſpect of the Illuminating, Conducting, Indwelling Godhead, to be equally applicable to his Humanity: this is plain from the Reaſons they give why they deny Chriſt to have a Divine Nature. The firſt is this, two Subſtances endued with oppoſite Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties cannot combine into one Perſon, <hi>i. e.</hi> [according to their Senſe of the word <hi>Perſon</hi>] into one individual Intelligent Eſſence. Nothing oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curs throughout the Biſhop's whole Diſcourſe contrary to this Negative; but to eſtabliſh it more ſure, ſeveral Expreſſions of the Biſhop's [as Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> of <hi>Kilmington</hi> has obſerv'd upon him] intimate that the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of Chriſt is a Perſon diſtinct from the Eternal Word that dwelt in him. 2. The Racovians deny the Divine Nature of Chriſt, becauſe [ſay they] two Natures, each whereof is apt to conſtitute a ſeveral Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>i. e.</hi> a ſeveral individual Intelligent Eſſence, cannot be huddled into one Perſon, or one individual Intelligent Eſſence. One would think that this Reaſon ſhould not down with the Biſhop, and indeed the Language does not; for <hi>p.</hi> 102. he ſays that from the Divine and Human Nature united, there did reſult the Perſon of the Meſſias: but then what does he
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:52170:19"/>
mean by <hi>the Divine and Human Nature united?</hi> Why, no more than <hi>The Human Nature always actuated, illuminated, and conducted by the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine.</hi> This is very agreeable to Scripture, yes, and the Racovian Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm alſo. But to make this look more like an unintelligible Union, that the Realiſts might not charge him with betraying the Cauſe to the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians, he calls it in lofty Phraſe, an <hi>aſſuming the Man into an inward and immediate Oeconomy,</hi> p. 108. In ſhort, the Biſhop makes no more of the Divine Nature than this—Chriſt was God by virtue of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dwelling of the Eternal Word in him, <hi>p.</hi> 127. The Racovians ſcruple the Phraſe, <hi>Divine Nature,</hi> but admit all that the Biſhop makes of it. The Biſhop places the Divine Nature in that thing, which the Racovians do not deny; and the Racovians deny the Divine Nature, for Reaſons which the Biſhop allows to be Truths: ſo then the difference between them is purely Nominal, a meer Logomachy. But to do his Lordſhip juſtice, he is in the right for uſing the Terms, <hi>Divine Nature,</hi> and <hi>God-man,</hi> becauſe they are Terms authoriz'd by the Church, on which both his Lordſhip and the Church puts an honeſt Senſe: and the Racovians were too ſtiff in refuſing them, eſpecially conſidering that in their very Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm they ſpeak, in other Phraſe, as honourably of Chriſt as his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; for they ſay, that Chriſt is by no means to be reputed a meer Man, they give their Reaſons for it, and therefore call him a Man truly Divine: and for my part, I think a Man truly Divine, muſt have a Nature truly Divine; and therefore the Racovians, whoſe Doctrine is taught by the Biſhop, would have done better had they taught it in the Terms of Art which the Biſhop uſes, tho perhaps he is not fond of the Terms, which one may partly gueſs by his declining to conſider all or any Speculations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Eternal Generation: Whereas the Unitarians fully to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate their Orthodoxy, allow the Eternal Generation of the <hi>Logos,</hi> Son, or Wiſdom. Let me not forget that I obſerv'd the Biſhop did not ſo well agree in one ſmall reſpect with the Unitarians, which reſpect was ſuch, that therein he was at ſome ſmall variance with himſelf: the thing is this, He has affirm'd that God and Man make one Perſon, as the Soul and Body make one Man; it was proper for him to take up with this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, in conformity to the Athanaſian Creed: but his Philoſophical Reaſonings look quite another way; for, <hi>p.</hi> 102. he has theſe Words, <q>It has been thought that the Human Nature in Chriſt had no ſpecial Subſiſtence, tho it was not eaſy to explain this Notion, ſince if Subſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence belong'd to the Human Nature, it might ſeem that it <hi>[the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Nature]</hi> was not perfect if it had not a proper Subſiſtence. An Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtatical Union was propoſed as a Term fit to explain this by, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Human Nature in Chriſt was believ'd to ſubſiſt by the Subſiſtence
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:52170:19"/>
of the Word; but it was not eaſy to make this the more intelligible, by offering a Notion full as unintelligible as it ſelf to explain it by.</q>
Now tho the Biſhop is a cautious Man, and will have a care of offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Brother, as appears by thoſe ſoft ways of expreſſing his diſlike of an Opinion—<hi>It has been thought—It is not eaſy—It might ſeem;</hi>—Yet here he ſufficiently diſcovers to any conſidering Reader, that he believes the Human Nature of Chriſt had a proper Subſiſtence; and if it had a proper Subſiſtence, then [ſay I] by it ſelf it conſtituted Chriſt a Perſon, and then God and Man did not make one Perſon, as the Soul and Body make a Man: For the Biſhop explains Subſiſtence thus, <q>We may conceive the Subſiſtence of an intelligent Being,<note place="margin">P. 107.</note> to be its acting intirely in it ſelf, or upon Matter united to it, without any other Spirit's being conſtantly preſent to it, actuating it, or having it under any immediate vital and inſeparable Influence.</q> It may ſeem ſtrange tho that the Biſhop ſhould intimate, that the Human Nature of Chriſt had a proper Subſiſtence, a Subſiſtence of its own, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards define the Subſiſtence of an Intelligent Being, to be its acting in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely in it ſelf, without any other Spirit's being conſtantly preſent to it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is a Mercy that Self-contradiction is not Hereſy. I hope the Biſhop is not of <hi>Rhetorius</hi>'s Mind, who thought that the Teachers of contrary Doctrines were all in the right. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> could not perſwade himſelf that any one could be ſo whimſical, but upon the Suppoſition he puts down the Name of <hi>Rhetorius</hi> in his black Catalogue of Hereticks.</p>
            <p>I deſign'd to have ſpoke at large with the Bp of <hi>Sarum</hi> concerning the Satisfaction of Chriſt, on which Article he can have no difference with the Unitarians, and has as little as may be with the Racovians; but the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of <hi>The Agreement,</hi> &amp;c. having been before me, I ſhall be the ſhorter. There is not a more artful controverſial piece of Writing, than ſome few Pages of the ſecond of the four Treatiſes. His Lordſhip's Learning and piercing Judgment are ſuch, that he clearly ſees through the whole Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, and no Man were better able to ſtate it plainly, to diſintangle it from the Philoſophy of the Schools, to decide it accurately, and firmly eſtabliſh the certain Truth: but then his Wiſdom is ſuch, that while he gives forth his Lectures, which may be very profitable to them that know how to uſe them, he retreats from the envy of the Calviniſts in a ſet of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Phraſes, whoſe ſtrict Grammatical Senſe has been long laid aſide; he diſtinguiſhes himſelf from the Racovians by labour'd Metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Flouriſhes, frowns upon the Unitarians to hide his Agreement with them, and amuſes the Writers of poſitive Divinity, [which Character he can tell any Party was not meant of them] to diſſemble his averſion from
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52170:20"/>
their unreaſonable and odious Scheme. I will convince the Reader of the Juſtneſs of my Obſervation. The Racovians diſpute againſt their Doctrine, who determine that there is ſuch a Mercy in God as muſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give, and ſuch a Juſtice as muſt puniſh, and cannot be ſatisfied without it; that becauſe God would have both his Mercy and his Juſtice take place, therefore he found out that way to forgive Sins, by ſending his Son to ſuffer Death in that Nature which had offended. Theſe Racovians acknowledg God to be wonderfully merciful and juſt, but they contend that he freely forgiveth, that he puniſheth Sins when he pleaſeth, when his Wiſdom thinks fit. Now let's hear the Biſhop; he ſets his Face againſt the Writers of <hi>Poſitive Divinity,</hi> and cenſures theſe their Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines, <q>That God cannot freely forgive Sins; that puniſhing, as well as remunerative Juſtice,<note place="margin">P. 135.</note> are eſſential to him; that God being infinite, every Offence againſt him has an infinite Guilt, and muſt be expiated either by Acts of infinite Value, or of infinite Duration; and that a Perſon of an infinite Nature was only capable of Acts of an infinite Value; that ſuch a one was neceſſary for the expiating Sin.</q> And are not theſe the very Errors oppos'd by the Racovians? more fully and elegantly ſtated by his Lordſhip, that's true, for nothing loſes under his hand; nor do the Racovians overthrow theſe Errors with that irreſiſtible force of Argument as his Lordſhip. For, ſays he, <q>In all this Gradation there is one main Defect, the Scripture ſets none of theſe Speculations before us; nor is it eaſy to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, that a Right of puniſhing which is in the Legiſlator, and a Right to reward, which paſſes from him to the Perſon that acquires it, ſhould be equally eſſential to God: in the one his Fidelity and Juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice are bound, becauſe of the Right that accrues to another; but the other of puniſhing, ſeems to be a Right that is veſted in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, which he may either uſe or not, as he pleaſes.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Agreeing thus in the main, one would wonder what Nicety ſhould divide the Racovians and his Lordſhip: there muſt be but a Nicety be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them; but 'tis not the firſt time a Nicety has made a great Breach between Friends. The Biſhop, ſpeaking of his Racovian Friends, pretends to take Diſtaſte, becauſe they believe <q>That Chriſt only died for our Good,<note place="margin">P. 141, 142.</note> and not in our Stead, that by his Death he might fully confirm his Goſpel, and give it a great Authority — They believe, That by his dying, he intended to ſet us a moſt perfect Pattern of bearing the ſharpeſt Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings with the perfecteſt Patience — and the moſt entire Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity — that by doing this he was to merit at God's hand that ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:52170:20"/>
Authority with which he is now veſted for our Good, that ſo he might obtain a Power to offer the World Pardon of Sin upon their true Repentance. Finally, That he died in order to his Reſurrection, and for giving a ſenſible Proof of that main Article of his Religion.</q>
Now what does his Lordſhip believe more than this? Why he ſays the ſame things over again in a new Set of Phraſes, and adds this Expreſſion, Chriſt ſuffered both <hi>upon our Account,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 143.</note> and <hi>in our Stead.</hi> If the Biſhop would abide by the ſtricteſt and moſt proper Senſe of theſe Words <hi>In our Stead,</hi> he would indeed differ in a conſiderable matter from the Racovians, but then he would alſo differ as much from himſelf; for he means no more by ſuffering <hi>in our ſtead,</hi> than the Racovians mean by ſuffering <hi>for our good;</hi> as appears from what he ſays p. 135. <q>If every Sin, as being of infinite guilt, muſt be expiated by an infinite Act, it will not be eaſy to make this out, how the Acts of Chriſt, tho infinite in value, ſhould ſtand in a ſtrict equality with all the Sins of ſo many men, every one of which is of infinite guilt.</q> If his Lordſhip is ſincere in this, then he cannot pretend to believe that Chriſt ſuffer'd the infinite Puniſhment due to the infinite Guilt of all Men, and by doing ſo, made a full, proper, and adequate Satisfaction for the Sins of the World; which is the ſtrict and proper Senſe of ſuffering in our Stead. All that his Lordſhip does, or can conſiſtently to himſelf, make of this Phraſe—<hi>In our Stead,</hi> is, That Chriſt did ſo ſuffer for our Good, that if he had not ſuffer'd as he did, we muſt have been the miſerable Sufferers our ſelves. But there is another Phraſe wherein his Lordſhip labours to diſtinguiſh himſelf from his Friends, and that is, <hi>Expiatory Sacrifice.</hi> But he may pleaſe to conſider, That the Racovians are not utterly averſe from this Phraſe; for in their Catechiſm, to that Queſtion, What think you of thoſe Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices? [<hi>i. e.</hi> of the Old Covenant] they anſwer, p. 139. <q>By them the Sins of the People were expiated or aton'd; that is, by the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening of thoſe Sacrifices, Remiſſion of Sins, graciouſly decreed by God, was brought to effect.</q> Otherwhere alſo they thankfully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg, That the Death of Chriſt expiates our Sins, through the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Condeſcenſion of his Father, who is pleas'd to accept that Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, not as a Payment to his Juſtice, but as an Application to his Mercy. And juſt thus, but more elegantly [as always] his Lordſhip explains what he means by an Expiatory Sacrifice, p. 151. <q>We are to conſider, that in Sacrifices it is the Appointment, and the Acceptation, which makes the Satisfaction; for God's accepting a Sacrifice, is an Abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Rigour of Juſtice, and a declaring that he will pardon Sins
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:52170:21"/>
in ſuch a Method and upon ſuch a Conſideration.</q> He had ſpoke to the ſame purpoſe, p. 136. But I am weary of tranſcribing. By what I have ſaid it is plain, That on the Article of Chriſt's Death, and Satisfaction for the Sins of Mankind, there is no real Difference between the Biſhop and the <hi>Racovian</hi> Catechiſm: and when his Lordſhip explains his leſs proper Phraſes, there's an end of all verbal Difference between them.</p>
            <p>As before of the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> ſo now of the Biſhop of <hi>Sarum,</hi> I have one thing to beg in behalf of the Unitarians: But becauſe I would not offer my Petition rudely, I have a very pertinent Story to introduce it. In the beginning of the laſt Reign, <hi>William Pen,</hi> in behalf of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and Friends, preferred an Addreſs, which to the beſt of my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance was thus worded.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>James,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>We are ſorry for the Death of thy Brother <hi>Charles,</hi> but we rejoice that we are fall'n under thy Government. Thou art a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſo are we; we hope thou wilt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low us that Liberty which thou tak'ſt thy ſelf. So farewel.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>By this excellent Pattern I draw up my Petition.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lord of Sarum,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>The Unitarians are ſorry that they have been miſunderſtood by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but they rejoice to find that your Lordſhip teaches the ſame Doctrine which they have done: If your Lordſhip thinks it no Hereſy in your ſelf, they hope it will be none in them. So farewel.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Having thus ſhewn by what Methods the Unitarians defend their Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines of evil Tendency and miſchievous Conſequence, I think it fit to acquit my ſelf of a Promiſe to Mr. <hi>Edwards.</hi> He takes notice of theſe Words in the <hi>Agreement, &amp;c.</hi> p. 7. <q>He may, for our parts, be <hi>Anathema</hi> that teaches or believes that Doctrine, <hi>viz.</hi> That there is no Merit in what Chriſt did or ſuffer'd, and that he made not Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for our Sins.</q> And he pretends that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary was taught by an Unitarian t'other day in theſe Words,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antitrinitarian Scheme,</hi> p. 18.</note> 
               <q>The Oblation which Chriſt made of himſelf, was not made to the Juſtice of God, or by way of Reparation, but, as all other Sacrifices, by way of humble Suit.</q>
Now I take this Paſſage to be ſo far from a Contradiction, that it may be look'd upon as a juſt and reaſonable Explication of the former. The Biſhop of <hi>Sarum,</hi> either more honeſt or more diſcerning than Mr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,</hi> repreſents the <hi>Socinians</hi> owning that Chriſt by his Death merit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at God's hands, merited a ſupreme Authority, and obtain'd a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to offer the World Pardon of Sin upon their true Repentance, p. 142. He believes alſo, with the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> that the Oblation was made,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:52170:21"/>
not to the Juſtice, but to the Mercy of God; for he ſays, pag. 135. <q>The Right of puniſhing, God may uſe, or not uſe, as he pleaſes; and that the Acts of Chriſt, tho infinite in value, cannot ſtand in a ſtrict Equality with the Sins of Mankind.</q> And whereas Mr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> accuſes the Unitarians for ſcoffing and ridiculing the Merits and Satisfaction of Chriſt, they are ready to tell him, 1. That they are the leaſt given to ſcoffing of any Writers of Controverſy. 2. It cannot be pretended that they have ſcoff'd the Merits and Satisfaction of Chriſt, as the Church and the Biſhop of <hi>Sarum</hi> underſtand thoſe Words, whatever they may have done to the Calviniſtical Hypotheſis, which Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> muſt embrace, if on this Subject he diſputes againſt them. 3. Whether the Calviniſtical Hypotheſis be fit to be ſcoff'd at, I will not argue; but I am ſure it deſerves to be abhorr'd. That there was no ſuch Juſtice in God, as neceſſarily oblig'd him to exact a Satisfaction, is a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion not only built upon ſound Reaſon, but alſo credited with the Authority of the moſt eminent Theologues, antient and modern: <hi>Voſſius,</hi> in his Anſwer to <hi>Ravenſperger,</hi> has quoted above a dozen of them, and <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Zanchy</hi> are two of the number. But Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> I will not ſay refines, but corrupts the very Dregs, the four Hypoſtaſis, the heavy Subſidence, the thick Sediment of Calviniſm.</p>
            <p>I thought I had concluded the Topick on which I have dwelt (I fear) too long already; but I beg the Reader's Patience yet farther, that I may call to mind a Gentleman who has engag'd in this Controverſy, and might take it ill if he ſhould be neglected, as one not worthy of our Notice.</p>
            <p>He is a zealous Accuſer, and a ſtrong Juſtifier of the Doctrine of the Unitarians; but ſince his Courteſy is more beneficial than his Anger in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious, tho perhaps he never intended it ſo, I will do what I can to reconcile him to himſelf. He is an irreconcilable Enemy to the Unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, or Socinians (as he calls them) of <hi>New Atlantis</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topia,</hi> but accords perfectly well with the European Unitarians, both Foreign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Engliſh. He ſaith p. 58 <q>There is a Diſtinction made in the Godhead, under theſe three Names, Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, which the Church hath expreſt all together by the Word <hi>Trinity,</hi> and ſingly by the Word <hi>Perſon.</hi>—I conclude that there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than a meer Nominal Diſtinction.— I conclude that they are not three diſtinct different Spirits.</q> From theſe two Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions let's hear what he infers, p. 59. <q>I infer there is in the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head ſomething more than a meer nominal Diſtinction, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs than that of three different Spirits.</q> Some Men have ſuch
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:52170:22"/>
roving wild Heads, that they'll infer any thing from any thing; becauſe the Moon ſhines with Light borrow'd from the Sun, therefore Kings hold their Crowns of the Pope: But our Author keeps cloſe to the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and infers from his two Concluſions, nothing but what he had concluded before. Well! if he is right in his Concluſions, he is ſafe in his Inference. But how came he by his Concluſions? Why, from ſome Paſſages of Scripture he found that there was a Diſtinction in the Godhead. Well! be it ſo. One might ask now, what is the Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction? Is it a Diſtinction of Properties, Relations, Modes, or what? But for that we muſt hold him excus'd; for (ſays he) <q>I have not the leaſt knowledg how ſtrict the Union is, or how great the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinction.</q> He was well ſet on work then, to write againſt the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Unitarians, who oppoſe no Trin-Unity, but a Trinity of Three diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct Eſſences, in Numerical Unity.</p>
            <p>But the Ignorance of this pert Academian is a ſmall Fault in reſpect of that cenſorious and ſingular Boldneſs wherewith he takes upon him to cenſure his Superiors in the Church; his Superiors for Learning and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity both, who ſeveral of them have attempted to explain, and have made it intelligible [at leaſt they themſelves think ſo] how the Three are diſtinguiſh'd, and how united. Mr. <hi>Peter Brown</hi> fears not to throw this Cenſure on their Undertakings; p. 59. <q>Any Man who ſtrives to conceive it himſelf, or takes pains to explain it to others, is guilty of ſuch a Folly, that I can't think of any Action in nature extravagant enough to match it.</q> This is very agreeable to his Senſe, p. 173. where he intimates that neither Dominion nor Religion are founded in Reaſon. So then his Loyalty and Orthodoxy are both of a piece. Our Church of <hi>England,</hi> in the late Reigns, had much ado to be loyal enough for the Men of <hi>Dublin;</hi> I am afraid they will have much ado to be Orthodox enough for them now.</p>
            <p>Having now ſpoke what I had to ſay concerning the Cauſes which have rais'd the Diſputes at preſent agitated among us, I am next to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what has inflam'd them to that dangerous Exceſs which in time may diſturb the publick Peace.</p>
            <p>Certainly it cannot be pure Love of God, or a ſincere Deſire to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the Happineſs of Mankind, which makes Religious Diſputants ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage their Controverſies with that angry impatient Heat: I know 'tis not uncommon for Men to pretend the Honour of God, and the Intereſt of Holy Religion, when they whet their Tongues like Raſors, and dip their Pens in Gall; when they lay Plots to oppreſs and kill, and are bent on Ruin and Deſtruction: nay, 'tis poſſible for them, while they are
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:52170:22"/>
thus miſchievouſly imploy'd, to think they are doing God Service, but they muſt have prodigiouſly debauch'd their Reaſon, before they can enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſuch Thoughts; for it is not eaſy to believe that God delights in Uncharitableneſs, Envy, Hatred and Perſecution.</p>
            <p>It is not eaſy to believe that Perſecution is not contrary to the obliging good-natur'd Precepts of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>It is not eaſy to believe that Force is the way to convince Men of their Errors.</p>
            <p>It is not eaſy to believe that Force is a proper way to move Men to conſider.</p>
            <p>It is not eaſy to believe that ſpeculative Opinions which Men cannot help, ſhould be deſtructive of their Eternal Happineſs.</p>
            <p>It is not eaſy to believe that the Magiſtrate's Sentiments are rational and true, meerly becauſe they are the Sentiments of thoſe who are in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>It is not eaſy to believe that the Magiſtrate has a right to enforce his own Opinions, when himſelf is confeſſedly liable to Miſtakes.</p>
            <p>It is not eaſy to believe that God would be worſhipp'd in every Nation only by that way which the Magiſtrate ſhall chuſe.</p>
            <p>It is not eaſy to believe that 'tis the Duty of Men to worſhip God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their Conſciences.</p>
            <p>Is it not eaſy to believe that Perſecution, which naturally tends to ſet all Mankind together by the ears, to deſtroy Trade and Commerce, and to hinder the Improvements of Knowledg, can be doing God good Service.</p>
            <p>It is not eaſy to believe that Magiſtrates were appointed to ruin thoſe for whoſe good, we are told in Scripture, they were ordain'd.</p>
            <p>It is not eaſy to imagine, that Authors who have publickly profeſs'd that in Matters of Faith every Man muſt judg for himſelf, and that every Man uſing his own Judgment, without Pride or affectation of Singularity, is doing the beſt thing that he can do; that ſimple Error is not Hereſy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it is not eaſy, I ſay, to imagine that ſuch Authors can eſteem Perſecution a part of that reaſonable Service which they owe to the Great God.</p>
            <p>If Men of reviling perſecuting Tempers could be perſwaded delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately and ſeriouſly to examine their own Minds, and put themſelves the Queſtion, What is it which prompts them to give bad Language, to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniate, to form Deſigns againſt the Fame, Eſtate, Liberty, and Life of their Brother, to purſue him beyond this Life, [not as <hi>Brutus</hi> did <hi>Aruns,</hi> which was the Wit of the Hiſtorian] but with real Enmity to purſue him beyond this Life, to hang him and burn him in order to damn
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:52170:23"/>
him; no doubt they might perceive that they were not mov'd by a true Love of God, or a deſire to advance the Happineſs of Mankind, but by an undue Love of themſelves, and a deſire to advance ſome not very ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Intereſt, which might be much impeded by an indulg'd Liberty of Propheſying: 'tis ſomething of this kind which has mingled ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bitter Reproaches, falſe Stories, and malicious Inſinuations with our controverſial religious Pleadings. That I may avoid the envy of deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Particulars, I leave my Obſervation, as it is propounded only in general, being ſatisfied that free impartial Conſiderers will ſoon perceive its Truth; and as to thoſe Perſons who are leſs us'd to look into the Reaſon of things, I will for their ſakes cover it with a great Authority: Bp of <hi>Sarum</hi>'s 4 Tracts, <hi>p.</hi> 185. <q>If it be ſaid that Error does diſturb the Peace and Order of the Church beyond what is to be apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Sin; Error runs Men into Parties, and out of thoſe Factions do ariſe, which break not only the Peace of the Church, but the whole Order of the World, and the quiet of Civil Society; whereas Sin does only harm to thoſe who are guilty of it, or to a few who may be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by their ill example: To this it is to be anſwer'd, That Sin does naturally much more Miſchief to Mankind than Error. He that errs, if he is not immoral with it, is quiet and peaceable in his Error; therefore ſtill the greateſt Miſchief is from Sin, which corrupts Mens Natures thro its own Influence. And the Miſchief that Error does pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, ariſes chiefly from the Pretenſions to Infallibility, or ſomething that is near a-kin to it: for if Men were ſuffer'd to go on in their Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, with the ſame undiſturb'd quiet that they have for moſt of their Sins, they would probably be much quieter in them; ſince Sin of its Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is a much fiercer thing than a point of Speculation can be ſuppos'd to be: but if Men apprehend Inquiſitions or other Miſeries, upon the account of their Opinions, then they ſtand together and combine for their own defence; ſo that it is not from the Errors themſelves, but from the Methods of treating them, that all thoſe Convulſions have ariſen, which have ſo violently ſhaken Churches and Kingdoms.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I quote no other Author, nor no more from this to the Purpoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, purely to avoid being tedious; but there is that plenty of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring Teſtimonies obvious to be collected from the printed Diſcourſes of the moſt eminent of our Eccleſiaſticks, that hardly a conſiderable Man of any order can call for the Sword of the Magiſtrate to puniſh Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of Opinion in Matters of Faith, but he muſt do it in defiance of his own Conſcience, as well as the Laws of the Land. I lay it down then, not only for a very certain, evident, but alſo for a generally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:52170:23"/>
Truth, that it is always a Vice, more or leſs artificially conceal'd, which prompts religious Diſputants to fight the Lord's Battels with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Noiſe, and fiery Words, and flaming Cenſures, that Thunder and Lightning of theirs, which does more Miſchief than all the Artillery of Nature from the ſtormy Sky, or the ſulphureous Caverns of the Earth.</p>
            <p>And now there's no avoiding the Inquiry, Whether the Unitarians or their Adverſaries, or both, have manag'd their Diſputes with any of theſe unjuſt and unbeſeeming Methods. It is urg'd hard upon the Unitarians that they have ridicul'd the venerable Articles of the Chriſtian Religion, and ſpoke diſreſpectfully and contemtuouſly of the moſt eminent learned and pious Fathers of the Church: for proof of the firſt Charge, the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Dulcinea,</hi> and one or two Paſſages more; of the ſecond, the two Tracts, call'd, <hi>Conſiderations of the Explications,</hi> &amp;c. are much inſiſted on. But methinks what the Unitarians ſay for themſelves in their own Defence, is weighty: as much of it as has been communicated to me, I will ſet down, and add what more is obvious, and may be juſtly added; but for the evener Thred of Diſcourſe, I offer both the one and the other as from my ſelf.</p>
            <p>I have ſcarce met with that Perſon who has read the <hi>Conſiderations,</hi> but confeſſes, thoſe two Tracts may paſs for Models of elegant, proper, and decent Writing, in the controverſial way; and I was amazed that two Reverend Biſhops ſhould think themſelves affronted or diſreſpected there; for my part I know not how a greater Deference could have been paid them, unleſs they had been honour'd as inſpir'd and infallible Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters, and worſhipp'd with Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi>'s groſs Flattery, which hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows their Names, and makes them ſignify <hi>profound Learning, and ſolid Religion.</hi> The ſevere Vertue of one of the old Romans, would have reſented this as a Libel: But however Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> vouches his elevated Compliment with a ſolemn Aſſeveration, <q>Without the leaſt ſhew of Adulation it may be moſt truly ſaid, that your Name is now not ſo much the Name of a Perſon or Family, as it is the Name of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Learning and ſolid Religion.</q> He that makes no conſcience of ſuch Strains and ſuch Vouching, tho to a Biſhop very Learned and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox, would have bated nothing had his Patron's Merit been no great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than his own. But I digreſs—The briskneſs and ſaltneſs in thoſe two Tracts, the <hi>Conſiderations,</hi> has nothing that is perſonal, nothing that reflected on the Perſons of their Lordſhips, or of any other Antagoniſts: it is no more than is allow'd to all Writers, that their Books may not nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeate an ingenuous Reader, or weary and tire the more Delicate by a continued Chain and Courſe of ſevere and cloſe Reaſoning, like a high
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:52170:24"/>
Tragedy, without any Interludes of Muſick and Dancing. And perhaps if their Lordſhips had leiſure to look into their former controverſial Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, when they were engag'd with other Adverſaries, they might find that themſelves had us'd as much Liberty as here they condemn. A long deduced Narration of Argument upon Argument, naked Argument, without pleaſing turns of Wit, or well-ſuted Ornaments of proper and manly Rhetorick, is a very dry Buſineſs, of which their Lordſhips have been ſo ſenſible, that when I was a young Fellow, I us'd to read their Writings for my Pleaſure as well as my Profit; and I will undertake to prove that in the controverſial Diſcourſes which they have publiſh'd in Print, whether againſt Papiſts or other Diſſenters from the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> they have us'd the Perſons of their Adverſaries more diſreſpectfully and contemtuouſly than it can be pretended the <hi>Conſiderer</hi> has us'd them; ſo that were their Charge againſt the <hi>Conſiderer</hi> juſt, they ought to forgive him for their own ſakes. It is a good Spaniſh Proverb, If a Man's own Houſe be made of Glaſs, he ſhould have a care of breaking his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour's Windows.</p>
            <p>But that which is aggravated moſt invidiouſly againſt the <hi>Conſiderer,</hi> is, the manner of his Reply to the late Archbiſhop; to expoſe which the Bp of <hi>Worceſter</hi> repeats what he pleaſes, without its Dependance and Connexion, and then pronounces, <hi>Pref. p.</hi> 54. <q>The plain meaning of all this is, that the late Archbiſhop was a <hi>meer</hi> ſelf-intereſted Man.</q> But if this be not the plain meaning, no, nor the meaning plain or obſcure; then the <hi>Conſiderer</hi> is falſly accus'd. I will lay the matter before the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. The <hi>Conſiderer</hi> begins his Anſwer to his Grace the late ArchBp, with an Apology for his undertaking to anſwer ſo many Men of the firſt Order in the Church, eminent for real Worth and excellent Learning: He expreſſes a particular Deference to his Grace, as he ought, above all the reſt. He then declares the Motives which perſwaded him to anſwer; this being done, that his Cauſe might not loſe by the Meanneſs and Obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his Perſon, he ingeniouſly notes, that in the Commonwealth of Learning, there's no regard had to Titles of Honour; wherefore if he has prov'd his Point, it avails his Oppoſers nothing that they are great Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners of the World, biaſs'd by Rewards, and Aws. It will indeed hence follow, that the <hi>Conſiderer</hi> did mean that in his Judgment, the Honours and Profits enjoy'd by the ArchBp, might have ſome influence on his mind to hinder him from diſcerning plainly the ſtate of the Queſtion, or freely ſpeaking his Mind: but this can never be made to ſignify that the ArchBp was a <hi>meer</hi> ſelf-intereſted Man, but by ſuch a Figure as makes the Name of a Learned and Religious Perſon truly ſignify <hi>profound
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:52170:24"/>
Learning and ſolid Religion.</hi> 'Tis not the moſt uncommon thing in the World, for good Men, in great Places, to be influenc'd ſometimes and in ſome things by ſelf-intereſt; but a meer ſelf-intereſted Man is one who is wholly govern'd by ſelf-intereſt, whoſe Opinions alter as his Intereſt does, whoſe Stile accommodates it ſelf to the Changes of Times, and the Steps of his own Advancement. But tho I am ſatisfied that the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderer</hi>'s Words do not reflect on the ABp. ſo injuriouſly as the Biſhop of <hi>W.</hi> would perſwade, yet I think it had been better that they had been unſaid, for they are off from the Argument, unbecoming, and beſt excus'd by obſerving, that none of all his Antagoniſts but has more to anſwer for upon this account than he.</p>
            <p>As for that Charge of ridiculing the Articles of the Chriſtian Religion, the Unitarians ſtand upon it, that they are perfectly innocent; only they acknowledg that they have wrote ſatyrically againſt the Heatheniſh Error of the Realiſts: but they hope they may be forgiven their Endeavours to put Tritheiſm to open Shame, eſpecially becauſe they never wiſh'd to ſee it hang'd or burn'd.</p>
            <p>I have now noted what may be juſtly pleaded on behalf of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians, to acquit them from the Guilt of an undue management of the Controverſy: but there are two things wherein I cannot excuſe them; the firſt is a piece of Raſhneſs and Indiſcretion; the ſecond, a Treſpaſs againſt a diſtinguiſhing Precept of the Chriſtian Religion. The Story of <hi>Dulcinea</hi> is pointed not againſt the Orthodox Doctrine, but the Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtick Unſcriptural Terms of the Nominaliſts. Now it was a piece of Raſhneſs and Indiſcretion to ridicule thoſe Terms (how obnoxious ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever) unto which, for Peace ſake, they now confeſs their Conſciences could ſubmit. Sure they could not hope that the old Scholaſtick Terms ſhould be laid aſide at their Inſtance. <hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> thought not amiſs of the Reformation which <hi>Luther</hi> drove at; but that it ſhould be made at the Inſtance of a pitiful Monk, ſeem'd to him intolerable. The Treſpaſs againſt a diſtinguiſhing Precept of the Chriſtian Religion, of which I think the Unitarians are in ſome meaſure guilty, is, That when they have been odiouſly miſrepreſented, foully calumniated, maliciouſly expos'd, haughtily inſulted, rated, revil'd, and cenſur'd by this and t'other Adverſary, better skill'd at Libelling than Logick, they have not taken it with all the compos'd Firmneſs of Mind, with all the ſteddy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience which the Commands of the Holy Goſpel requir'd, and the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of their bleſſed Maſter made practicable; but when they have been barbarouſly us'd, have anſwer'd angrily again. It's true, the worſt Returns that they have made, compar'd with what they have ſuffer'd,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:52170:25"/>
may ſeem perfect Courtſhip; but if they had never been mov'd from an even Chriſtian Temper when all manner of evil was ſpoke againſt them without juſt Cauſe, their Labours would have gain'd a ſtill higher Eſteem, and perhaps have been handed down to late Poſterity, as the moſt abſolute Patterns of a dexterous and able, pertinent, cloſe, and juſt Management of Controverſy.</p>
            <p>I ſhould now examine how the Controverſy has been manag'd by thoſe Authors who have oppos'd the Unitarians, whether upon the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Tritheiſm, or upon a miſunderſtanding of one another about certain Terms of Art which admit divers Conſtructions: But I am really afraid of examining this, well knowing that I ſhould meet abundance of Unchriſtian Matter, not capable of any favourable Repreſentation. Should I but ſhew how they have treated one another, the impartial Reader would certainly ſay, that the Unitarians ought to ſit down content under the Injuries which have fall'n to their ſhare: and therefore I hope theſe Authors will give me leave to paſs them over [all but one, who has diſtinguiſh'd himſelf by peculiar Antichriſtian Exceſſes] with this general, not harſh Cenſure. In ſome of their Writings there appears much Learning; ſo much Learning, that it runs into Confuſion; ſuch Confuſion, that tho you may perceive whom they love, and whom they hate, yet you cannot eaſily divine what Opinions they are for or againſt: in others there are to be met better digeſted Learning, and a ſtrong Viva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of Wit. This Man deſpairs of ſolving the Difficulties he meddles with, but honeſtly hopes, that one time or other a lucky Interpreter will riſe, that preſumes he has ſtarted a Notion which <hi>ſeems to give ſome light to help to form ſome general Idea</hi> of Matters in queſtion; but among them all, there's little or no Chriſtian Moderation and Temper. Yet if theſe great Perſons had confin'd themſelves to cloſe Reaſoning, and left the zealous angry part to Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> their Cauſe would not have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd for want of calling Names. That worthy Author's Book, entit'led <hi>A brief Vindication of the fundamental Articles of the Chriſtian Faith,</hi> is ſuch an entire piece of Railing, that no <hi>Rabſheka</hi> before Chriſt, nor <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> ſince, ever equall'd it. 'Tis wrote too all in the Strain of <hi>Bombo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machides-Cluninſtaridy-Sarchides,</hi> Great <hi>Neptune</hi>'s Grandchild: I van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh'd the ſtupendous Giant <hi>COL,</hi> ſprung from the prolifick putrefying Gore of the odious Leviathan; we fought on <hi>Altercando</hi>'s Plains, where <hi>Lana Caprina</hi> has ſo often committed Fools and Philoſophers together. I puſh'd hard at firſt; in vain the mighty Monſter roar'd, in vain diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorg'd his poiſonous Replies; for now collecting all my Powers into one impetuous Volume, I pour'd in upon him 500 bald Reproaches,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:52170:25"/>
Conundrums, and Blunders innumerable; and to perfect the glorious Work, I murder'd his Fame, but that, with ſome few trifling Stories, two malicious Witticiſms, and one lewd obſcene Alluſion. I ruin'd the whole <hi>Poſſe</hi> of the Unitarians, ſtruck their choſen Champion dead, that Champion that was cull'd out of the whole Hoſt, and was himſelf an Hoſt, or elſe he had not been a Match for me; yet him I confounded only with ſome Scores of Perverſions, and a few bolder Falſifications of Authors. I chain'd the Rector of <hi>Steeple</hi> to the Carcaſe of old <hi>Malmſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury;</hi> like another <hi>Mezentius,</hi> I clap'd them together, <hi>Componens ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibúſque manus, atque oribus ora:</hi> And thus I made an One-Article Chriſtian ſtink alive.</p>
            <p>The wonderful Book, full of theſe Strains, borrows all the Credit which it can from an Univerſity-Licence. This calls to my Memory an Obſervation formerly ſent me by a Friend. The Spaniſh Clergy have the Reputation of learned and judicious Divines all over <hi>Europe;</hi> not that they really excel thoſe of other Countries, but becauſe the Pride and Gravity of the Nation takes a particular Method which procures them this Fame: they will not ſuffer every ſplenetick Trifler to ſcandalize his whole Order, by publiſhing his paſſionate Ignorance or Weakneſs to the World from the Preſs; they abſolutely refuſe to licenſe any but very good Books. By this Policy of theirs, a Spaniſh Divine is become but ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Phraſe for a very learned and judicious Divine. This is a dext'rous way of raiſing a vaſt Reputation to a Community from a ſmall ſtock of Merit: our Univerſities might make their Advantage of it, but if they are for ſetting all hands to work, then Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> ought not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd his humble Requeſt. But this notwithſtanding, I will ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what for his <hi>Brief Vindication;</hi> that is, If it had not been for one thing, it might have repaid the Kindneſſes of the Licencers: for if all that part of it, which was meant for reaſoning, had been downright railing, and the railing part reaſoning, perhaps the reaſoning would have been weak, becauſe his Head is diſorder'd, but the Book would have been a very ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Book. But indeed as it is, I defy all the Hereticks in Chriſtendom, and all the Atheiſts in the World to write any thing ſo wicked and unchriſtian. I reſerve the Conſideration of Particulars, till he publiſhes ſuch another Book; for I reckon, that tho he has in all manner of evil-ſpeaking far out-done Hereticks and Atheiſts, yet 'tis not impoſſible, but that having ſucceeded ſo ſtrangely in this unchriſtian Sally, he may adventure again, and out-do himſelf. But as for the Unitarians, if I were fit to adviſe them, they ſhould never concern themſelves any more with this Author. Mr. <hi>Lock,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bold</hi> are in equal Prudence oblig'd to let him rail on.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:52170:26"/>
There's a Story in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> the Subſtance of which I remember, but the Book I have not by me; ſome Strangers from <hi>Chios,</hi> debauch'd lewd Fellows, full of Wine and Madneſs, vomited in the Court of the <hi>Ephori,</hi> the chief Magiſtrates of the City, nay, and did ſomething worſe in the very Chairs of State. Inquiry being made after the ſhameleſs Offenders, and Information giv'n in, every one expected to have ſeen them ſeverely handled; but the <hi>Ephori</hi> contented themſelves with ordering their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Crier to proclaim, That the Gentlemen of <hi>Chios</hi> ſhould have leave to be as filthy, impudent, and wicked, as their wretched baſe Natures would prompt them.</p>
            <p>I ſhall have abſolv'd my Deſign, when I have added what occurs to my Mind concerning the proper way to remedy the Miſchiefs which have happen'd from the Controverſy, and to prevent farther. One would think it were eaſy to remedy ſuch Miſchiefs, and to prevent the like for the future, becauſe in the controverted Points themſelves, there is ſo fair and full an Agreement between the Orthodox Nominaliſts, who are the Church, and the no leſs Orthodox Unitarians. Eager Diſputants ſeldom convert one another; but many times, after long Diſpute, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover that they raſhly fell out, and that there was no material Difference between them. Thus it is in the caſe before us; but then a very odd thing happens upon it; for the Parties are like to fall out again, becauſe they fell out before for nothing. I am inform'd, that ſome angry No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaliſts threaten to call the <hi>Conſiderer</hi> to account, for giving the Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Quarrel, and proteſt that they do not mean to be trick'd out of the Puniſhment of Hereſy by a Turn of Wit. So the <hi>New Juſtice</hi> (if I remember right) in one of Old <hi>Ben</hi>'s Plays, upon every Rap at his Gate he bid his Clerk run, and bring the Malefactors in, that he might draw their <hi>Mittimus.</hi> What! no Malefactors yet? <hi>O Tempora! O Mores l</hi> But I thought it had been the Office of a Miniſter of the Goſpel, to preach the Mercies of God in Chriſt, to teach, to exhort, to declare God's Judgments againſt Sin, not to execute them; to win Men to God, not to ſend them to the Devil; for God reſerves the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Vengeance to himſelf, and therefore allows the Civil Magiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate no coercive Powers farther than to preſerve the publick Peace, which is unconteſtably prov'd in that admirable, ſtrong, clear, and convincing Tract, entitled, <hi>An Eſſay concerning the Power of the Magiſtrate, and the Rights of Mankind in Matters of Religion;</hi> for which the learned Author deſerves a Statue in every Kingdom and Commonwealth upon the Face of God's Earth.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:52170:26"/>
            <p>No Men can be in love with ill Uſage, and therefore the Unitarians remonſtrate, That they were always perſwaded that they had theſe two ways to prove their Doctrine Orthodox, 1. The Suffrage of Reaſon; 2. The Teſtimony of Scripture; but now they have a third, the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Nominaliſt Unitarians, and they are reſolv'd to make the moſt of it. They like the Doctrines they have always taught never the worſe for their being reaſonable; they are tenacious of them, becauſe they are Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural; and not a little pleas'd to ſee, that the Nominaliſt Trinitarians have expounded the Articles of the Ch. of <hi>England</hi> to the very ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Would the latter recant their Expoſitions, which are Unitarian all over, I would not enſure the former <hi>ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> à reatu ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> poena,</hi> nor from the Guilt, nor from the Puniſhment of Hereſy: but as the caſe ſtands, they have but one thing to anſwer for, and that is, affronting ſome receiv'd Terms of Art; for which Offence, to ſay the truth, they have giv'n but little Satisfaction; for ſtill they prefer Scripture Phraſes before all other, ſtill they look upon the received Terms of Art as ill choſen and improper, and conſent, not to oppoſe them, only for Peace ſake, and not out of any Reverence which they are willing to pay to the Inventions of Philoſophick Fathers, or the critical Fancies of ſubtle Schoolmen. Indeed this Fault, let it be never ſo much aggravated, will not make out a very honorable Pretence for Eccleſiaſtical Execution, and yet 'tis the beſt that can be had, unleſs the <hi>Perſecutors</hi> ſhould chance to light upon the arbitrary Device, of taking upon them not only the Interpretation of the Articles of the Church, but alſo of the Writings of the Unitarians. By this means indeed the Unitarian Writings might chance to appear Heretical, that is, unleſs the <hi>Perſecuted</hi> ſhould fall into the Humour of appealing to all impartial and unprejudic'd Perſons, whether the Writings of the Nominaliſt Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians be not as obnoxious as theirs, and altogether as much at the mercy of an Interpreter. And perhaps there be, that think the World has been troubled too much by them both, and that neither ought to be forgiven, unleſs they firſt forgive one another; and I am ſtrangely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, if I cannot name the Inſtances, which duly conſider'd, recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to them both ſo much Humanity.</p>
            <p>The Nominaliſts are ſafe from the Unitarians, not only by the Unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Principle which diſavows Perſecution, but alſo becauſe of their Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city; nor can their Abilities make them formidable; for, as a great Man notes, their Adverſaries are their Superiors both in Wit and Learning: and the Unitarians ought to be ſafe from the Nominaliſts, not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:52170:27"/>
the Doctrine of them both is one and the ſame, tho their Language ſometimes varies, but alſo for thoſe many cogent Reaſons which are to be met with, in the <hi>Eſſay</hi> above cited, and in the Letters for Toleration; which I preſume will have their influence on both Nominaliſts and Realiſts, as many of them as are men of Vertue, true Piety, and Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Moderation; but as for ſuch furious Inquiſitors as Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Peter Brown,</hi> I reckon they are ſo very paſſionate, that they are ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly incapable of attending to ſober Reaſoning from plain Chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples: therefore I will tell them a Story, which perhaps they may have read in their younger days; and that it may not be thrown away upon them, I will be at the pains of application. <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> Prince of <hi>Epirus,</hi> an ambitious Politick Captain, made uſe of one <hi>Cyneas,</hi> a ſenſible witty Man, in the conduct of his weightieſt Affairs. This Perſon one day ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſted his warlike Maſter after this manner: The <hi>Romans,</hi> Sir, againſt whom we are arming, are a hardy valiant People; but if the Gods ſhould proſper us, how ſhall we uſe our Victory? Why, ſaid <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> when we have beaten the <hi>Romans,</hi> we ſhall preſently be Maſters of all <hi>Italy.</hi> And how ſhall we govern our ſelves then Sir? Then Sir! why then <hi>Sici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> holds out her Arms to receive us, a fruitful Iſland, a noble and an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy purchaſe. Very probable: and what! ſhall the poſſeſſion of <hi>Sicily</hi> put an end to the War? O Friend! ſays <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> we muſt not throw away the Opportunities which the Gods put into our hands. We are next bound for <hi>Lybia:</hi> and then <hi>Carthage,</hi> proud, populous, and wealthy, is ours: and by that glorious Conqueſt we ſhall become powerful enough to ſubdue all <hi>Greece.</hi> The ſubtle <hi>Cyneas</hi> ſtill plied him with the Queſtion, What are we for next? At laſt <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> replied, Then we'll live at Eaſe, ſpend our days in Wine and Mirth, and nothing ſhall employ our Thoughts but the ways to vary and heighten our Pleaſures. When <hi>Cyneas</hi> had brought his unwary Maſter to this point, he turn'd ſhort upon him, and ask'd, What hinders us now from living at Eaſe, without diſpoſſeſſing others of their Rights, and hazarding our own Fortunes? Inſtead of running all theſe Riſques, we may even now ſit down and ſing, <hi>O be Joyful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to my Application. Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> and Mr. <hi>Brown,</hi> furious Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in Polemic Squabble, ambitious both to ſpread their Empire wide over Conſcience, were one day in Conſult, how to remove the Obſtacles that ſtood in their way. The methods they agreed on, were, to reſtrain the Preſs for fear they ſhould loſe by diſputing, to cenſure what they do
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:52170:27"/>
not underſtand for fear there ſhould be Hereſy in't, to ſet up an Inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to jail the ſuſpected of Faith erroneous, and burn the avow'd Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter. Their firſt Proceſs they determin'd to direct againſt a handful of Men, of late known by the Name of Unitarians, in contradiſtinction to ſome Eccleſiaſticks profeſſing to believe and worſhip three diſtinct Infinite Minds. Dr. <hi>Chriſtian Eubulus</hi> was their Chancellor, whom they requir'd to proſecute the aforeſaid poor Men with the utmoſt Rigour. This <hi>Chriſtian Eubulus</hi> repreſented to them that the Unitarians held no private Doctrines, different from what were taught by our moſt Orthodox Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates; that they were Men of ſome Learning, untainted Probity and good Senſe; but if it was irrevocably decreed, that they were to be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly rooted out, he humbly deſir'd to know whom he was to fall upon next: Why! ſaid Mr. <hi>Edw.</hi> and Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> when we have once diſpatch'd theſe malepert Unitarians, we ſhall become formidable to all the Baw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers againſt Prieſtcraft, who now deſpiſe us, and need not be afraid to attacque the <hi>Quakers;</hi> of whom the largeſt Diviſion, the <hi>Foxonians,</hi> who are the ruling Party, are meer Deiſts; they are a numerous and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick People, the Scripture is to them a dead Letter, the Rule of their Faith is the Light within them, that is, meer natural Reaſon; and they have an odd way with them, inſtead of guarding their own Doctrines, they attacque ours; ſo 'tis abſolutely neceſſary to ruine this Sect: It may be done by Fines, Impriſonment, Death if need be, or merciful Baniſhment; What matter if the State loſe by it? bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be without them and their Effects, than plagu'd with their Hereſy. <hi>Chriſtian Eubulus</hi> ſeem'd to acquieſce, but deſir'd to know of his Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, whether they ſhould have any more need of him: O Dear Friend, replied they, when God has bleſſed our Zeal ſo far for his Service, we muſt not give over ſo; there are two Sticks, ſo they call themſelves, <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Independents,</hi> crooked Sticks both, who cudgel one another when we let them alone, but not enough to the purpoſe; theſe Sticks muſt be burnt, both burnt, for they will not bend to decent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline; and by that time we have conſum'd them to Aſhes, all the little crawling Sectaries will fall down and worſhip as many infinite diſtinct Minds or Eſſences as we pleaſe, or one ſuch infinite Mind in Language that ſignifies Three. <hi>Chriſtian Eubulus</hi> was again at his Queſtion, and when all the World conforms, What then? Then Man! replied the bold <hi>Duumviri;</hi> why then we'll live like true Chriſtians, none of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion ſhall be ſuffer'd to indulge himſelf in Prophaneſs and Immora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; we'll ſhow Mercy, and do Works of Charity; we'll diligently
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:52170:28"/>
preach the holy Doctrines of the Goſpel, and honeſtly practiſe them our ſelves; ſo that the Church ſhall become a Heaven upon Earth. When <hi>Chriſtian Eubulus</hi> had brought his zealous Maſters to this point, he put them the hard Queſtion of all; Why can't we live like true Chriſtians now? Why cannot we now diſcourage the Prophaneſs and Immorality of the Members of our Communion? What hinders us now from being fervent in Prayer, diligent in preaching the Goſpel, and exemplary in our Lives and Converſations?</p>
            <p>When one is got into Stories, eſpecially by the Parlour Fire in a Winter Evening, there's no end of them; but if the Reader will forgive me, I will puniſh him but with one more, and it ſhall be as ſhort as he could wiſh. <hi>Barclay</hi> in his <hi>Icon Animorum,</hi> tells us of a Father and his two Sons who excommunicated the whole World, and confin'd the Church within the narrow Pale of their own three Elect Perſons; within a few days the hopeful Boys excommunicated the old Man, and not long after they excommunicated one another. Suppoſe now the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſhould convert or confound the Unitarians, the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, the Presbyterians, the Independents, and every little Philadelphian Society; nay, and Popiſh Recuſants alſo, tho that's a ſwinging Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition: is all like to be Peace at home within her own Body? no ſuch matter, the Quinquarticular Controverſy will ſet 'em together by the ears among themſelves; Mr. <hi>Gailhard,</hi> and the <hi>Growth of Error</hi> have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready declar'd open War againſt all Churchmen of the Arminian Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; for want of a Bone, the Theory of the Earth will make a buſtle among them; and for ought I know the Royal Society may make ſome Diſcovery in Nature, that may be Hereſy in Religion: but to mention no more, the Unitarian Controverſy it ſelf ſhall live among them as vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous as ever; Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> will never forgive Dr. <hi>South;</hi> nor Dr. <hi>South,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock;</hi> the Nominaliſts will never leave till they have run down the Tritheiſts; the Tritheiſts with their laſt Breath will revile the Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naliſts for Sabellians and Socinians: ſo that in ſhort, if the Church will have no War without her Pale, ſhe muſt have one within; wherefore I would adviſe every one to make living like a good Chriſtian his Buſineſs now, and never be troubled at the Diſputes which are ſtirring, of which there's like to be no end, let the preſent Diſputants that have the worſt on't, by reaſon of their inferiour Numbers, be run down, hang'd, or burnt, or not.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:52170:28"/>
            <p>I conclude with one word of Advice to the Unitarians, <hi>i. e.</hi> that they would give over the Diſpute; I know they are Men of Conſcience, and have, within the Bounds of Moderation, been zealous for the Truth, but that will not ſuffer, tho they are ſilent; the Learned and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Biſhops of <hi>Worceſter</hi> and <hi>Sarum,</hi> Dr. <hi>South</hi> and others are able and forward enough to defend it againſt all the heatheniſh Oppoſition of the Tritheiſtick Tribe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
